<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discovery of the most dangerous dead faith by John Eaton ...</title>
            <author>Eaton, John, 1574 or 5-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69920</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23218</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12494188</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12494188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62458</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69920)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62458)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 210:5 or 1568:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discovery of the most dangerous dead faith by John Eaton ...</title>
                  <author>Eaton, John, 1574 or 5-1641.</author>
                  <author>Eaton, John, 1574 or 5-1641. Abrahams steps of faith.</author>
                  <author>Eaton, John, 1574 or 5-1641. True treasure of the heart.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second impression</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[26], 200 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Bishop for William Adderton, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 210:5 incorrectly identified as Wing E113, and at reel 1568:29 identified as Wing (CD-ROM, 1996) E114.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62458:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62458:1"/>
            <p>THE DISCOVERY of the <hi>most dangerous</hi> Dead Faith. <hi>BY</hi> JOHN EATON, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, and ſometime Student in Trinity Colledg in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and 15. yeers Miniſter and Preacher at <hi>Wickham-Market</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi> The ſecond Impreſſion, with an Addition of <hi>Abrahams Steps of Faith,</hi> and <hi>The true Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Heart.</hi> By the ſame Authour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Biſhop</hi> for <hi>William Adderton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Duck-lane</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62458:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62458:2"/>
            <p>THE DISCOVERY of the <hi>most dangerous</hi> Dead Faith. <hi>BY</hi> JOHN EATON, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, and ſometime Student in Trinity Colledg in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and 15. yeers Miniſter and Preacher at <hi>Wickham Market</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Heb. 2. 12.</bibl> Take heed brethren, leſt there be in any of you an evill heart of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, in departing away from the living God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Biſhop</hi> for <hi>William Adderton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Duck-lane</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:62458:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62458:3"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE elect veſſel of God, St</hi> Paul, <hi>gave two ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and cleare prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of things to be fulfilled before the ſecond comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: the first, of the riſing, reigne, and fall of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, as he ſaith,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2, 3, 4. <hi>that</hi> the day of Chriſt ſhall not come, except there come
<pb facs="tcp:62458:4"/> a falling way firſt (<hi>to wit, from faith</hi>) and that man of ſin be revealed, the ſon of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who oppoſeth and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe above all that is called God, or that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; ſo that he, as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelfe that he is God. <hi>Concerning whom</hi> the Spirit ſpeaketh expreſly, that in the latter times men ſhall depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and doctrines of devils, ſpeaking lies in hypocriſie, having their conſcience ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with an hot iron, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to marry, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to abſteine from meats
<pb facs="tcp:62458:4"/> which God hath ordained, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim. 4. 1, 2, 3. All which we now ſee to be in theſe latter times clearely revealed and plainly fulfilled, and that</hi> the man of ſin is conſumed with the Spirit of Chriſts mouth (<hi>that is, the Word of God</hi>) and ſhall be deſtroyed (<hi>to wit, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly</hi>) with the brightneſſe, or glory of his comming, 2 Theſ. 2. 8. <hi>The other Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie followes this, plainly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing theſe our laſt daies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the truth of the Goſpel being againe reſtored, and the purity of faith againe profeſſed; yet people ſhould be ſuch ſleepy em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracers of the ſame, and ſuch dead, unprofitable, unfruitfull,
<pb facs="tcp:62458:5"/> atheisticall, and unthankful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and profeſſors of it, that theſe laſt dayes ſhould bee farre more perillous and dangerous than the former; Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, although ſome ſeeme to conjoyne it as all one with the former (which for the neer fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing one of another may beare the more eaſie interpretation:) yet Saint</hi> Paul <hi>doth distinguiſh them, and plainely ſever this later from the former, as being for time the later, yea in the laſt dayes, and for nature, the more perillous and dangerous; and therefore he ſaith, not in the later times, as in the former Propheſie. But this know (ſaith he) alſo that</hi> in noviſſimis, <hi>or</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62458:5"/> extrem is diebus, in the laſt dayes <hi>of all</hi> ſhall come <hi>hard and</hi> perilous times: <hi>Wherein hard and perilous? Becauſe (ſaith he</hi>) men (<hi>namely, ſuch as profeſſed themſelves reformed Christians</hi>) ſhall be lovers of their owne ſelves, covetous, boaſters, or braggers, proud, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, unthankfull, unholy, without naturall affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, or make-bates, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, traytors, heady, high-minded, lovers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures more than lovers of God. <hi>Muſt it not needs bee a very hard and dangerous living
<pb facs="tcp:62458:6"/> in theſe laſt dayes with ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous generation as theſe. But that which followes after is more hard and dangerous (namely</hi>) having a forme of godlineſſe, but denying the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, 2 Tim. 3. <hi>to the 5. Marke, I pray, that herein lieth the great perill and danger of theſe laſt dayes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (that is) having the forme, ſhew, and appearance of faith, piety, and true godlineſſe, they deny, or are farre from the truth, vertue, or power of faith and godlineſſe, having indeed neither faith, nor love; and ſo are not only overwhelmed themſelves in the moſt dangerous dead faith, to the fearfull deceiving, and utter
<pb facs="tcp:62458:6"/> destruction of their own ſoules; but alſo doe ſo dangerouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrap the very elect in this dead faith, that (if it were poſsible) the very elect might finally bee deceived, and periſh therein. And hereby for a time may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, becauſe they doe not mark that there are two ſorts of ſuch as are in this dead faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt ſort are ſuch (and thoſe very many) as being borne and brought up in the outward viſible Church, can talke of Chriſt, and of ſome generall points of God, and his Goſpell, ſaying that they hope to be ſaved by Chriſt, becauſe they thinke that they beleeve, and are of that true Religion that all their
<pb facs="tcp:62458:7"/> Countrey is of: but being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the horrible filthineſſe of ſin before God, and of the infinite pure and righteous nature of God againſt ſin, and thereby ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and careleſſe of free ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, that only heales them, doe continue in their old cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt natures, and are</hi> Crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees, <hi>bringing forth only</hi> the ſower and bitter Crab-apples <hi>of a prophane life, and a ſecure, and careleſſe, looſe converſation: who though they ſooth and flatter themſelves in this ignorant dead faith, and hope they ſhall doe well enough, or at leaſt as well as their neighbours; yet doth God by the Prophet</hi> Eſay <hi>denounce againſt them, ſaying,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62458:7"/> It is a people of no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, therefore he that made them will have no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on them; and he that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them will ſhew them no favour, <hi>Eſay</hi> 27. 11. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hell hath enlarged her ſelfe, and opened her mouth above meaſure, and their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and their multitude, and their pomp, and hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth ſhall deſcend into it, <hi>Eſay</hi> 5. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other ſort that are in this dead faith, are ſuch as ſeeme to be awaked out of this dead le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie, and profeſsing a better feeling of ſin, and a deeper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their loſt eſtate and miſery by ſinne, aſpire with a
<pb facs="tcp:62458:8"/> ſtronger deſire, and a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter earneſtneſſe to life and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But becauſe they are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally conceipted, that the meanes to attaine this life and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to leave their ſinne and to become good, holy, juſt, and righteous: therefore they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect free justification, the only true meanes and way to life and ſalvation; and ſet light of faith in Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which doth perfectly juſtifie before God, and are carried with a blinde prepoſterous zeale after their owne good workes and well doings, ſecretly ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to become good, holy, juſt, and righteous before God, by their diligent keeping, &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:62458:8"/> walking in all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; and ſo by a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal underſtanding of juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are carried away from Chriſt, and true free justification, to hang upon their own good works and well-doings; and thereby instead of life and free ſalva<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, doe drowne themſelves in ſinne, death, and eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and yet under a deepe conceit of great holineſſe and righteouſneſſe. And thus doe they periſh with the devout un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving Iewes, who although they had a blinde, dead faith of righteouſneſſe, life and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse by the</hi> Meſſiah <hi>to come; for they</hi> did all eat of the ſame ſpirituall meat, and did
<pb facs="tcp:62458:9"/> all drinke of the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall drinke, (<hi>that is, by this generall dead faith in Chriſt to come</hi>) for they dranke of that ſpirituall Rock that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them, and that Rocke was Chriſt. But God was not well pleaſed with them (<hi>in this dead faith</hi>) and ſo they periſhed, 1 Corinth. 10. 3. to 6. <hi>And yet S.</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith of them,</hi> that they followed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Law of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but yet did not attaine to the Law of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Wherefore? Becauſe they ſought (<hi>the keeping and fulfilling of it) not by faith,</hi> but as it were by the workes of the Law; and ſo ſtumbled
<pb facs="tcp:62458:9"/> at the ſtumbling ſtone, Rom. 9. 31, 32. <hi>Yea, Saint</hi> Paul <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth and</hi> beareth record of them, <hi>that herein</hi> they had the zeale <hi>even</hi> of God, but not according to knowledge <hi>of free juſtication.</hi> Becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to eſtabliſh (<hi>or to make, as it were, to ſtand upon its feet</hi>) their owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>and ſo</hi> did not ſubmit themſelves to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God; <hi>And thus they periſhed, becauſe they knew not that</hi> Chriſt was the fulfilling and end (2 Cor. 3. 7, 8, 11. 14.) of the Law for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth,
<pb facs="tcp:62458:10"/> Rom. 10. 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus we ſee that ſuch as are in this dead faith, varni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and garniſhed, and gilt over with this preposterous zeal of diligent keeping, and carefull walking in all Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are ignorant of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, the maine of their free-ſalvation; are unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, onely giving Chriſt and free juſtification a</hi> Judas his kiſſe, <hi>whereby they goe about to ſtabliſh, or ſet up (as it were) upon its feet their owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe wiſh the Iewes and Phariſees, and contemne and ſet light of free Grace, are rebellious against God, in not ſubmitting themſelves to
<pb facs="tcp:62458:10"/> the righteouſneſſe of God, and miſerably periſh (as I ſaid) in the deepe conceit of great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe, which doth ſo ſtrongly bewitch the people with a faire glister, and beautifull brightneſſe of workes of righteouſneſſe, that it cunningly creepes up into the Pulpits alſo, and with her faire ſhew turneth the Miniſters of Satan into the ſeeming Ministers of Christ,</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 13, 14, 15. <hi>As Chriſt ſaid to the Angel of the Church of Sardis,</hi> Thou beareſt a name that thou liveſt, but thou art dead, Rev. 3. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So that although both theſe ſorts of the dead faith doe reject
<pb facs="tcp:62458:11"/> and ſet light of free justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and are both enemies to free grace, the glory of Chriſt, and to their own free ſalvation: yet doth this ſecond ſort more ſubtile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceive, and more dangerouſly destroy. And therefore the first ſort of people in this dead faith are by the</hi> Lord of wiſedome Jeſus Chriſt <hi>likened to</hi> Hogs, <hi>that having the</hi> pearle of the Goſpel, <hi>free justification, caſt before them to call them from their</hi> rooting in the earth and wallowing in the mire <hi>of ſin; although they</hi> contemptuouſly trample this onely ſaving pearle under the filthy feet of their careleſſe and ſwiniſh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: <hi>Yet they commonly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:62458:11"/> their Miniſters, and them that wiſh them well, do only give</hi> a hoggiſh grunt of contempt, <hi>and away they goe to their</hi> root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their earth, <hi>or</hi> to their wallowing in the mire, <hi>and ſo are plainly diſcerned, ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, and many of them eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier converted and ſaved. But the ſecond ſort are likened to</hi> Dogs, <hi>that</hi> greedily feeding upon the carrion of their good workes, <hi>obedience, and well-doings: if any caſt before theſe the</hi> precious pearles of Chriſts works <hi>and well-doings, as ſufficient perfectly to juſtifie them, and freely and certainly to ſave them, they do not only</hi> tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under the feet of their
<pb facs="tcp:62458:12"/> Phariſaicall affections the ſame precious pearls; <hi>but alſo fall,</hi> like Dogs, abarking <hi>at them that wiſh them well, with calumniations, railings, and ſlanderings: Yea, through a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inbred delight, and blinde zeal of eſteem of the hidden vain glory of their own righteouſneſs, good works, obedience, and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doings, contrary to the Prophet</hi> Eſay <hi>and</hi> Pauls <hi>affection, that counted all the righteouſneſſe, works, and wel-doings of their ſanctification but as</hi> filthy ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned rags, and would not bee found in them <hi>before God, but</hi> eſteemed them as dung, that they might bee found in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt <hi>only
<pb facs="tcp:62458:12"/> before God,</hi> Phil. 3. 8, 9. <hi>Through this ſecret lurking vain-glory I ſay) of their owne holineſſe and well-doings, they will not ſtick to flye in the face of the Minister and</hi> Meſſenger of Chriſt <hi>that</hi> beſeecheth them to be reconciled unto God <hi>by</hi> being made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of God through Chriſt <hi>only,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 20, 21. <hi>but will</hi> teare <hi>out, if they can, his very</hi> throat; <hi>becauſe they feel them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves hindred from feeding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the filthy pleaſing</hi> carrion <hi>of the vaine glory in their owne works of righteouſneſſe and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doings. And therefore did the Apostle ſay to the true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> Beware of Dogs, Phil. 3.
<pb facs="tcp:62458:13"/> 2, 3. <hi>becauſe in ſtead of life and ſalvation, which they ſeeme ſo ſtrongly to aſpire unto by works, and keeping the Law, they ruſh the more violently themſelves, and ſwiftly carry away others with them into beautifull abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, ſinne, death, hell, and everlaſting damnation. So gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily with</hi> Aeſops <hi>dog as Doctor</hi> Luther <hi>ſaith) ſnatching at the outward glittering ſhadow of righteouſneſs of works, that they loſe the ſubſtance of Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe that is in their mouth. Therefore, happy is the man that in theſe laſt ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous dayes can overcome, and eſcape this Dead Faith, by get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the</hi> white robe, that he
<pb facs="tcp:62458:13"/> may be clothed, and that his filthy nakedneſſe doe not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and doth annoint his eyes with eye-ſalve that hee may ſee, <hi>and ſo become zealous, not with the foreſaid blind, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall zeale of his owne glory, but with the true Evangelicall zeale of Christs glory; and ſo amend by comming out of this Dead Faith into the true lively ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifying faith. For,</hi> to him that overcommeth <hi>this Dead Faith (ſaith Chriſt</hi>) will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as I alſo overcame, and am ſet down with my Father in his throne. He that hath an eare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith unto the
<pb facs="tcp:62458:14"/> Churches, Revel. 3 18. <hi>to 22. And for this cauſe have I pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this ſhort and abrupt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe diſcovering this moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Dead Faith, in ſhewing how farre it will goe in the likeneſſe and appearance of true Christianity, and true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith, and yet how farre it comes ſhort of the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they doe not</hi> beleeve with the heart unto true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, <hi>and</hi> confeſſe <hi>the ſame</hi> with <hi>a thankfull and joyfull</hi> mouth unto ſalvation, Rom. 10. 10. <hi>and ſo doe ſhew by their bragging Phariſaicall life, that they periſh with the</hi> Famine in their Hearts, whilſt the fleſh of qauiles is
<pb facs="tcp:62458:14"/> in their mouths, <hi>Pſalm. 78. 30, 31. And hereunto I have adjoyned the ſhorteſt courſe that the Word of GOD, and the eſtabliſhed Doctrine of our Church preſcribeth, how wee Miniſters may our ſelves come out of this most dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> DEAD FAITH, <hi>and call others out of the ſame into the true lively and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith.</hi> Try all things, and keepe that which is good, 1 Theſſalon. 5. 21. <hi>And accept Chriſtianly in good part the good will of him that is glad</hi> (Chriſtian READER) <hi>if hee may ſpeake or write a word that may</hi> edifie thee in thy moſt holy Faith, <hi>Iud.</hi> 20.
<pb facs="tcp:62458:15"/> 
               <hi>Vſe it in the feare of GOD. And thus I leave thee to the Word of his Grace which is able to build fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian affection, JOHN EATON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62458:15"/>
            <head>THE DISCOVERY Of the <hi>Most Dangerous</hi> Dead Faith.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt divers and ſundry cauſes of peoples being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at, and of cavilling againſt the expreſſe Word of God, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants deſcription of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62458:16"/> Wedding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe, by which the juſtified perſon is made ſo truely, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly holy and righteous from all ſpot of ſinne in the ſight of God, that God doth, and (by his actuall power) can ſee no ſin in his juſtified children freely by faith one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without workes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 18. The chiefeſt cauſe of all their cavills, containing in a manner, all the reſt, is the Dead faith; it being not able to underſtand the myſteries of Chriſt, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth to the carnall Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, ſaying, <hi>the naturall man receiveth not the things of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62458:16"/> the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 14. For the removall of which Dead Faith, four main things are here eſpecially to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, we muſt mark how far the Dead Faith will goe in the profeſsion of the Goſpel, and how like it is to the true, lively, juſtifying, and ſaving faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as like the true faith, both in it ſelfe, and in reſembling all the actions of the true faith, as the Image in the Looking-glaſſe is like, and doth imitate the party that looketh into the ſame; becauſe the Dead Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62458:17"/> of theſe three parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, ſuch as are in this Dead Faith, may have great knowledge of the whole word and will of God, and may joyne therewith the reading of all the Doctors and Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors in the Church, and alſo may be zealous Preachers of the ſame: as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 17. ſaying, <hi>Behold thou art called a Iew</hi> (that is, one of Gods choſen above all the Nations of the earth) <hi>and resteſt in the Law</hi> (that is, in the Word and Doctrine delivered from heaven) <hi>and glorieſt in God: And knoweſt his will, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provest the thing that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62458:17"/> being inſtructed in the Law,</hi> or Word, verſe 18. <hi>And art confident that thou art a guid of the blind, a light of them that are in darkneſſe,</hi> verſe 19. <hi>An inſtructer of the fooliſh, a teacher of the ignorant, having the whole forme of knowledge, and of the truth of the Law, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>the Law ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh from the Prieſt, nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell from the wiſe, nor the word from the Prophet. Come let us ſmite Ieremiah with the tongue,</hi> Jer. 18. 18. <hi>For wee have the adoption, and the glory, and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the promiſes,</hi> Rom. 9. 4. and ſuch like Scriptures
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62458:18"/> ſhewing great knowledge in this Dead Faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch may have a kinde of ſtrong faith in all Gods graces through Chriſt, and thinke that they beleeve them as well and as truely as any other, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach: <hi>Thou ſayest I am rich, and encreaſed with goods, and have need of nothing; but thou knoweſt not, that thou art wretched, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and poore, and blinde, and naked,</hi> Revel. 3. 17. Againe, <hi>When many beleeved</hi> Philip <hi>which preached the things that concerned the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and the Name of Ieſus: then</hi> Simon Magus
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62458:18"/> 
               <hi>himſelfe alſo beleeved, and was baptized, and continued with</hi> Philip, <hi>and wondered when he ſaw the ſignes and great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which were done,</hi> Acts 8. 12, 13. Againe, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I would not have you ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, Brethren, that all our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were baptized unto</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>in the cloud and in the ſea, and did all eat the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meat, and did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke; for they dranke of that ſpirituall Rocke that followed them, and that Rocke was Chriſt. But with many of them God was not well pleaſed, for they were destroyed in the Wilderneſſe, and periſhed,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 2. to 11. Thus we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62458:19"/> ſee that many bad gueſts doe ſit downe at the feaſt of the Goſpel, ſeeming in their own opinion to abound in faith and knowledge, to whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is wanting but only the <hi>not-having on the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Mat.</hi> 22. 12. Thus much of their ſeeming ſtrong faith.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, ſuch as are in this Dead Faith may have a kinde of great humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and earneſt repentance: As <hi>Ahab</hi> (though hee was a King) rent his cloaths in great repentance, and put on ſackcloth upon his fleſh, and faſted and lay in ſackcloth, and walked ſo mournfully, that the Lord the ſearcher of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62458:19"/> hearts ſaid, <hi>Seeſt thou how A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab humbleth himſelf before me?</hi> mark, <hi>before me,</hi> the Lord, and not before the world onely; and yet was <hi>Ahab</hi> one in this Dead Faith. And againe, as <hi>David</hi> in the true faith repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſaid, <hi>I have greatly ſinned in that I have done, and have done very fooliſhly.</hi> So did <hi>Saul</hi> in the Dead faith ſay, <hi>I have ſinned, and have done foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly, and have erred exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly: Thou art more righteous than I; for thou haſt rendred me good, and I have rendred thee evill, and hee lift up his voice and wept, 1 Sam,</hi> 24. 16, 17. &amp; 26. 21. Neither onely may ſuch have this great humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62458:20"/> and earneſt repentance, but alſo they may have a great zeale of Gods glory, and an earneſt endevour of holy and righteous walking in all Gods Commandements, as it is plainly declared, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 2, 3. ſaying, <hi>Yet they ſeeke me daily, and delight to know my wayes, as a Nation that did righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and forſook not the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of their God. They aske of me the ordinances of juſtice: They take delight to draw near unto God by prayer and faſting, and puniſhing and afflicting of themſelves.</hi> And this they may doe, not onely not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblingly and for vain glory and praiſe of men, as many
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62458:20"/> groſſe Hypocrites and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees did, mentioned <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. but as other Phariſees did of a good intent, ſo zealouſly ayming at Gods glory, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting their corruptions and ſins; and ſo fervently <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſneſse according to the Law of God, Rom.</hi> 9. 31. to the intent to be a holy people unto God by their workes and well-doings; that concerning prayer, and faſting, and all good works, and <hi>righteouſneſs of the Law they may be unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and many other Jewes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their converſion to the Goſpel, ſaying, <hi>I beare them record that they have the zeale
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62458:21"/> of God,</hi> Rom. 10. 2. <hi>Inſtantly ſerving God day and night,</hi> Act. 26. 7. <hi>So eagerly following the Law of righteouſneſſe, as it were by the works of the Law, Rom.</hi> 9. 31, 32. that concerning the <hi>righteouſneſſe of the Law they were unblameable,</hi> Phil. 3. 6. whereupon the Phariſee ſaid, <hi>I thank thee, O God, that</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſecond Table, <hi>I am no extortioner, nor unjuſt perſon, nor adulterer, nor as this Publican.</hi> And in the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Law, <hi>I am ſo zealous in thy worſhip, that I faſt twice in the weeke, and ſo carefull to maintaine thy ſervice and relief of the poore, that I give tithe of all that I poſſeſs,</hi> Luk. 18. 11, 12.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62458:21"/> And by this opinion of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and well-pleaſing of God, <hi>Paul</hi> being <hi>taught ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the perfect manner of the law of the Fathers, was ſo zealous towards God, as they were all at that time, that heper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Chriſtians unto death, binding and delivering into priſon, both men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Act.</hi> 22. 3, 4. And after <hi>Paul</hi> was converted, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, blind keeping of the law <hi>ſtirred up the devout and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable women, and the chief men of the City, and raiſed perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against Paul and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, and expelled both them and</hi> Chriſt himſelf with them, <hi>out of their coaſts, Acts</hi> 13. 15. Thus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62458:22"/> we ſee this firſt maine point proved, how farre the Dead faith goeth in humiliation, repentance, and zealous keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law, wherein they greatly appeare in outward profeſſion to themſelves and others, to bee zealous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the true faith of Chriſt: whereas in this dead faith, gilt and varniſhed over with a blind, legall zeale of keeping all Gods will and commandements, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly rather Jewes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout zealous Phariſees, than true ſaved Chriſtians. And thus much of the firſt point, how farre the dead faith will goe in the profeſſion of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62458:22"/> Goſpel, and how like it is to the true ſaving faith.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>The ſecond main point is, that now we conſider the plaine and evident marks whereby this dead faith may be diſcerned, and whereby it diſcovereth it ſelf to be naught in the three aforeſaid parts, and appearances of the true lively faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Firſt their foreſaid great knowledge before deſcribed is but literall, as is before deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 17. to 29. And they are ſo puffed up with their ſuppoſed great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 1. that they thinke they underſtand and know as much as any true child of God can know, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62458:23"/> and ſecretly abhorring to ſeem to learn any thing of any man: and yet they know nothing, neither the Law nor the Goſpel, neither faith nor works truely, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth, ſaying, Now <hi>if any man thinketh that hee knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet, as hee ought to know, 1 Cor.</hi> 8. 2. For they being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, men meerly conſiſting of a naturall ſoule, doe underſtand the benefits and myſteries of Chriſt after a carnall and humane-witted faſhion of underſtanding; and having not on the wedding garment, do hang upon works, &amp; ſtick faſt in the religion of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62458:23"/> reaſon, and in the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, deſcribed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15. ſaying, <hi>the Gentiles which have not the Law, doe by nature the things contained in the Law, which ſhew the workes and effect of the Law written in their hearts, their conſciences alſo bearing wtineſs, and their thoughts accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them,</hi> that is, with fear of puniſhment when they doe evill; and excuſing them, that is, with hoping to ſpeed well, when they doe well: here is the whole maine of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And doe thus draw o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from faith &amp; Chriſt, to hang upon works with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp; ſo make a number of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62458:24"/> ſects &amp; ſchiſms about works, turning all Goſpell it ſelfe into precept upon precept, and line upon line, <hi>Eſay</hi> 28. 10. and being fleſhly, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, not having the ſpirit, <hi>Iud.</hi> 19. Though they talke and glory greatly of it, yet they ſee not, and diſcerne not the ſpirituall and inviſible benefits wrought upon Gods Children by the blood of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 9. but onely (<hi>picarum inſtar</hi>) after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pies doe chatter of them: All their ſeeming great knowledge being meerely blindneſſe and darkneſſe: yea, (which is wonderful) none ſo blind as they; as theſe &amp; ſuch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62458:24"/> like Scriptures teach: <hi>Hear ye deafe, and regard ye blind, that ye may ſee: who is blind but my ſervant, and deafe as my meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger that I ſend? who is blind as the perfect?</hi> Eſay 42. 17, 18. Whereupon the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, <hi>Stay your ſelves and wonder,</hi> they are blind and make you blind; <hi>Therefore behold I will doe a marvellous work in this people, even a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous work, and a wonder. For the wiſdome of the wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of their prudent men ſhall bee hid. For the Lord hath covered you with a ſpirit of ſlumber, and hath ſhut up your eyes, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and your chiefe Seers hath
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62458:25"/> he covered,</hi> Eſay 29. 9. 10. 14. The reaſon whereof is becauſe <hi>they ſeeing doe not ſee, and hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring they doe not understand,</hi> Matth. 13. 13. whereby in them is fulfilled the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Eſay;</hi> ſaying, By hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring they ſhall heare, that is, they heare (as they thinke) perfectly, but ſhall not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; and ſeeing ye ſhall ſee, that is, they ſhall ſee (as they thinke) excellently well, but not perceive. For this peoples heart is waxed groſſe, and their eares are dull of hearing. And with their eyes they have winked, leſt they ſhould ſee with their eyes, and hear with their eares,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62458:25"/> and ſhould underſtand with their hearts, and ſhould returne that I might heale them. And yet they ſay, are we blind alſo? But Jeſus ſaid unto them, If you were blind, yee ſhould in compariſon have no ſinne; But now yee ſay, We ſee; therefore your ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth (double.) <hi>For I am come unto judgement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this world, that they which ſee not might ſee, and that they which (ſay they) ſee might bee made blind,</hi> John 9. 39, 40, 41. And yet by this blindneſſe they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating the faith, words and workes of the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62458:26"/> are ever ready preſt to <hi>call light darkneſſe, and darkneſſe light, good evil, and evil good,</hi> &amp; to put <hi>bitter for ſweet, and ſweete for bitter,</hi> Eſa. 5. 20. And thus much of their great knowledge that are in the dead faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meer blindneſſe as wee ſee.</p>
            <p>2. Secondly, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their faith. Although they ſeeme to have a ſtrong faith in the myſteries of the Goſpell, and to preach eloquently the benefits of Chriſt: yet they ſpeake prepoſterouſly, ignorantly, and confuſedly of them, ſaying, <hi>Sibboleth,</hi> but cannot
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62458:26"/> ſay <hi>Shibboleth</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when they ſpeake of them, they underſtand not what they ſpeake; all things in the plaine Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel being unto them in Parables, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Marke</hi> 4. 11, 12. therefore they will not onely in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Sermons, but often times in one and the ſame Sermon, or conference, if not in plaine words, yet in plaine ſenſe, ſpeake flat contraries, in and to the workes of Chriſt, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpel: and ſo ſay and unſay, ſaying one way, and unſaying, and denying the ſame things
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62458:27"/> againe another way. And thus doe <hi>ſee many things</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> 42. 20. ſaith) <hi>but keepe not</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in words nor deeds, <hi>to the cauſes,</hi> to the nature, or to the effects of the things which they ſeeme to ſee, grant, and hold. Becauſe <hi>though they be</hi> great <hi>Doctors, yet they know not what they ſpeake, nor whereof they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,</hi> and even (as it were) confidently ſwear to, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 7. eſpecially in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall benefits, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpell. And ſo are Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his double-minded men, toſſed to and fro, like a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62458:27"/> wave of the ſea, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable in all their wayes of Religion, and theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine nothing of the Lord, <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 6, 7, 8. And all their ſeeming ſtrong faith is indeed before God no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but meere unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, as Chriſt teſtifieth of ſuch, ſaying, <hi>There are ſome of you,</hi> (namely that profeſſe by beleeving that you are my Diſciples but ye <hi>beleeve not; For Ieſus knew from the beginning who they were that beleeved not, and who ſhould betray him,</hi> John 6. 64. And this dead faith being like a <hi>dead man,</hi> that cannot ſtay up himſelfe to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62458:28"/> ſtand upon his owne feet, nor reſt upon his owne ſtrength; they goe about to ſet him up, and to <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derprop this dead man,</hi> that is, this dead faith <hi>with the rotten ſtaffe of their workes.</hi> And hereupon giving but a flouriſh of praiſe now and then to faith in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; they being utterly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and void of true ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying and ſaving faith, doe dwell in, reſt upon, and ſtay up themſelves and their dead faith principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by workes. And hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doe in their hearts dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, and in their words magnifie, extoll, and extort
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62458:28"/> with legal arguments a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous ſanctification, repentance, mortification, grace, and graces Popiſhly and falſly underſtood; new life, holy and righteous walking, univerſall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, ſincerity, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, uprightneſſe, faſtings, regeneration, Popiſhly alſo and falſly underſtood; and ſuch like workes extorted (as I ſaid) with legall argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of I hope of rewards and ſpeedings well, if wee doe them; and with feare of puniſhments and ſpeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill, if we have them not: which how much the more
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62458:29"/> they are thus prepoſterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exacted and legally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted, ſo much the more under termes and titles of the Goſpell, ſuch Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers teach but the light of nature, the pride of workes, and the vain-glory of man; and ſo do withdraw people from Chriſt to hang upon their owne workes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, by reſting upon the Popiſh rotten pillar, that God accepts the will for the deed, and ſo doe drown Chriſts glory, free Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, doe deſtroy faith, waſte and conſume the Church of Chriſt, teach a falſe baſtard ſanctification,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62458:29"/> and are thoſe dangerous ſeducers of ſoules, that the faithfull are commanded (as they will continue chaſt Virgins to Chriſt, and not to bee beguiled with <hi>Eve</hi> by the ſubtlety of the Serpent, and ſeduced from the ſimplicity of their faith that is in Chriſt) to diſcerne and take notice of, as they are deſcribed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13, 14, 15. where the Apoſtle forewarneth, and thereby ſufficiently fore-armeth all the children of wiſdome by thus plainly deſcribing them. They profeſſe themſelves Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; that is, ſent forth of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62458:30"/> God: But they are (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) falſe Apoſtles, and they are great workers, but (ſaith hee) deceitfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers. How deceitfull? transforming themſelves (ſaith he) into the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Chriſt; that is, as if they were the true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and taught the true Goſpel of Chriſt: and no marvell; for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan himſelfe is transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into an Angel of light, and therefore it is no great thing if his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters transform themſelves, as though they were the Miniſters of 'righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; that is, calling ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62458:30"/> for all works of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. But their end ſhall be according to their workes and righteouſneſſe, that is, though they ſee me to bee the principall men that ſhall bee ſaved, yet the ſame Apoſtle threatens to them certaine deſtruction. Which he warneth of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that wee may not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve every ſpirit, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>try the ſpirits</hi> (by this deſcription) <hi>whether they bee of God, 1 Joh.</hi> 4. 1. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe are the wolves whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gave warning, <hi>Acts</hi> 20, 29. 30. that ſhould ariſe up out of the allowed Miniſtry, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62458:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62458:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62458:32"/> ſhould teach not ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſe things, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, prepoſterous things, or true things out of order, ſetting the cart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the horſe; that is, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring more to call for works and a good life, than they care whether the people have aſſurance of the ſound faith of their free and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Juſtification, whereby although the people beare them record, and applaud them, that <hi>they have the zeal of God; yet it is not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the knowledge</hi> of free Juſtification; <hi>Becauſe</hi> (by a carnall underſtanding of free Juſtification) <hi>they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62458:32"/> ignorant of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God,</hi> muſt needs <hi>goe about to ſtabliſh and ſet up the</hi> golden calf <hi>of their own</hi> and the peoples own <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> of their ſuppoſed ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, works, and well doings: and by thinking ſecretly in their heart with the Papiſt, that free Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is eaſily learned and is ready to open the gate to the people to live wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly and looſely, they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſlightly preach free Juſtification, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhew that <hi>they have not ſubmitted themſelves to the righteouſneſſe of God, Rom.</hi> 10. 2, 3. And ſo are the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62458:33"/> of Satan (as the true Proteſtants ſay) and are white Devils that preach a ſecret Idolatry under the likeneſſe of the true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel; and for darkning and giving a <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das his kiſſe</hi> to free juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation (which onely makes the true Church of Chriſt, and by which onely Chriſt reignes in his Church, as a free and glorious Redeemer and Saviour) doe ſtand <hi>ipſo facto</hi> accurſed of God, and excommunicated by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> though in all other gifts (and as they ſay gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) they bee like <hi>Angels from heaven,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62458:33"/> teſtifieth <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8, 9. And becauſe the greateſt multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of holy religious ones (in a cold love to Chriſt, and a hot love to themſelvs in their owne doings and vaine glory) care not to <hi>try the ſpirits whether they bee of God, or no, 1 Iohn</hi> 4. 1. therefore <hi>God ſends them</hi> (theſe zealous and holy working Preachers in the dead faith as) <hi>strong deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> Ezek. 14. 9. <hi>that they ſhould beleeve lyes and bee damned,</hi> becauſe <hi>they receive not the love of the</hi> truth of the wedding garment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely ſaving <hi>truth,</hi> Gal. 3. 1. to 8. <hi>that they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62458:34"/> might bee ſaved,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 10, 11, 12. and that onely <hi>makes us free,</hi> John 8. 32. And being freed from the bondage and ſervile yoke of works, that the children of God in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were under, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 23, 24, 25. and chapter 4. 1, 7. doth make us <hi>ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and not to be entangled in the ſaid yoke of bondage againe,</hi> Gal. 5. 1. whereas contrariwiſe, ſuch zealous legall Profeſſours, are either ſeeming humble, proud Phariſees confident in their owne well-doings, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 11, 12. or elſe ever
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62458:34"/> wounded in their ſoules, diſtracted into ſects, and troubled in their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about their life and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. And God in juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ingratitude of ſuch, doth ſuffer blind zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous leaders of the blind zealous multitude often times every where to ſwarm and abound, whereby both Preachers and innumerable people fall into the pit of deſtruction, as Chriſt the truth it ſelfe teſtifieth and denounceth, <hi>Matth. 15. 14. Let them alone, they be blind leaders of the blind: And if the blind lead the blind, both ſhall fall into the ditch,</hi> to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62458:35"/> wit, of deſtruction. And theſe are the traytours that under colour of greateſt friendſhip with God, and of lying in his very lap by working out their ſalvation, in diſtruſt, in free grace, and in truſt in their workes and well-doings, doe break our peace with God in this land, doe betray whole Kingdomes and Countries into their enemies hand. Becauſe they truely know not free juſtification, that only makes our peace with God, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Rom. 5. 1. Therefore being justified by faith, we have peace with God,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62458:35"/> &amp;c.</hi> this place being an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as it were of that ſaying, <hi>Num.</hi> 23. 21. ſpoken then but prophetically, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choatively, and typically at the lifting up of the braſen ſerpent, ſaying, <hi>God ſeeth no iniquity in Jacob, and he ſeeth no tranſgreſsion in Iſrael.</hi> This is to bee juſtified by faith. Then followes the peace and reconciliation that wee have therefrom. Therefore the Lord his God is with him, and the joyfull ſhout of a King is among them; that comes onely by free juſtification, which propheſie is now by Chriſt the ſubſtance (ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62458:36"/> by that braſen ſerpent) fully wrought and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletely exhibited and brought upon us in the new Teſtament, ſaying, <hi>And yee which were in times past ſtrangers and enemies in your minde by evill works, hath hee now reconciled:</hi> How? or by what means? <hi>In the body of his fleſh through death,</hi> by making you ſo holy that you are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without all blame and without all fault in Gods ſight: if you continue rooted and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this faith</hi> of free ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by Chriſts blood and death, <hi>and be not moved away from this hope of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62458:36"/> Col.</hi> 1. 21, 22, 23. But contrariwiſe, Chriſt <hi>weeping over Ieruſalem,</hi> denounced, that their enemies ſhould lay their city and them even with the ground, and <hi>not</hi> leave <hi>a ſtone upon another</hi> that ſhould not bee caſt downe; why? becauſe they <hi>knew not the things that did belong to their peace,</hi> that is, they knew not their recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation by Chriſt, they knew not his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to juſtifie them, which only makes peace with God: but <hi>theſe things were hid from their eyes,</hi> Luke 19. 41, 42, 44. Therefore did the Prophet ſay, For <hi>Zions</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:62458:37"/> ſake I will not hold my tongue, and for <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> ſake I will not reſt untill the righteouſneſſe thereof breake forth as the light: for then the ſafety and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thereof will be as a burning Lamp. And when the Gentiles, or people ſee thy righteouſneſſe and the Kings thy glory, thou ſhalt be a Crown of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a Royall Diadem in the hand of thy God: It ſhall no more be ſaid unto thee, <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken:</hi> neither ſhall it any more bee ſaid unto thy Lands, <hi>deſolate.</hi> But thou ſhalt bee called <hi>Hephziah,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62458:37"/> that is, my delight is in her, for the Lord will delight in thee, <hi>Eſay</hi> 62. For <hi>thy people ſhall bee all righteous, they ſhall poſſeſſe the Land for ever, the graffe of my planting ſhall be the work of my hands, that I may be glorified,</hi> Eſay 60. 21. Becauſe, <hi>as by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of one ſhall many</hi> (to the end of the world) <hi>be made righteous,</hi> Rom. 5. 19. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, if by one mans offence, the diſpleaſure, anger of God, and death reigned by one: much more they which receive that abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of grace, and that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62458:38"/> abundance of the gift of that righteouſneſſe, ſhall reigne in reconciliation, well-pleaſing of God, peace and life through one, that is, Jeſus Chriſt. That <hi>as ſinne</hi> had <hi>reigned unto</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, wrath, and death: even <hi>ſo</hi> might <hi>grace reigne</hi> by <hi>righteouſneſſe unto</hi> recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, peace, and <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life by Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Rom.</hi> 5. 17, 21. But contrariwiſe, they that are not juſtified by faith, have no peace with God: but by their dead faith are foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold traytours; namely, traytours to Chriſt and his Goſpel, traytours to his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62458:38"/> Church &amp; children, traitors to their King and countrey, and traytours to their own bodies and ſoules, ſeeming great friends to all theſe, but betraying every one of theſe with a <hi>Iudas his kiſse.</hi> Becauſe although they ſeem in this dead Faith, and blind zeale of the Law, and works, to be lifted up in as high a faith and happineſſe as any can be; yet if they do not come out of this dead faith when they dye, be it ſooner or later, they caſt down themſelves into greater damnation, than if they had never profeſſed Gods word and the Goſpel of Chriſt at all, as Chriſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62458:39"/> teſtifieth <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 23, 24. ſaying, <hi>and thou Capernaum that art exalted into Heaven,</hi> (namely in profeſſing Gods word) <hi>ſhalt be thrown down to hell: for if the mighty works which have beene done in thee</hi> (much more being profeſſed to bee received and beleeved of thee) <hi>had been done in Sodome, it would have remained untill this day: But I ſay unto you, it ſhall be more tolerable or eaſie for the land of Sodome in the day of judgment than for thee.</hi> And again, <hi>Wo be unto you Scribes and Phariſees hypocrites, for ye compaſſe ſea and land</hi> (that is, take exceeding great
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62458:39"/> pains and labour) <hi>to make one Proſelyte,</hi> (that is, one zealous Profeſſour, as you ſay, of the pure word of God, and holy worſhip of God) and <hi>when he is made, you make him twofold more the child of Hell than your ſelves, Matth.</hi> 23. 15. And thus much of the dead Faith, gilt over with the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall zeal of works, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of practiſing repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, humiliation, and all holy duties, by a ſuppoſed univerſall obedience to all Gods commandements: and yet all is but a falſe legall baſtard ſanctification.</p>
            <p>3. But now thirdly, which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62458:40"/> moſt of all diſcovereth this dead Faith, and blind zeale of the good workes of the Law to be meer ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hypocriſie, whereof Chriſt giveth warning to his Diſciples, ſaying, Firſt of all <hi>beware of the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, Luk.</hi> 12. 1. If the old matter of the pure Goſpel be uttered but after a new manner, otherwiſe than theſe like blind mill-horſes are accuſtomed to run round in: or if their literall knowledge, dead Faith, and blind legall zeale be any way a little croſſed, or but tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched (although a faithfull
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62458:40"/> Miniſter muſt needs teach <hi>novè,</hi> but not <hi>nova,</hi> that is after a new manner, but not any new matter) yet theſe humble ones, juſt like <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus, Ioh.</hi> 3. in that new manner of ſpeaking do riſe up againſt Chriſt, and count the old myſteries of Chriſt and of his Goſpel to be <hi>nova,</hi> novelties, new doctrines; as theſe ſaid when Chriſt himſelf began firſt to preach the old revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will of his Father, <hi>What thing is this? What new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is this? Mark</hi> 1. 27. Yea they count the ſame ſtark naught, and meer foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:62458:41"/> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, or the man of a meere humane ſoul percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not the things of the ſpirit of God, but they are fooliſhneſſe unto him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can be perceive them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. And becauſe they are not truly humbled to tremble at every word of God, to beleeve the ſame according as it is ſpoken, agreeable to the greatneſſe and majeſty of God the ſpeaker, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 18. And becauſe their foreſaid legall zeale of their holy work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is void of Chriſtian love and charity; therefore their feet are ſwift to picke
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62458:41"/> quarrels, to <hi>make a man an offender for a word, and to turn aſide the juſt for a thing of nought, Eſay</hi> 29. 21. And feeling their dead faith, and corrupt worſhip of God to be, as I ſaid, but touched; then their blinde zeale ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) the faith, words, and workes of true beleevers, boyleth forth into our-cries of errours, hereſies, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies: And moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Chriſt himſelfe ſhall among theſe not eſcape the black cenſure of being counted a ſeducer of the people, and a blaſphemer and troubler of the Church:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62458:42"/> thus vilely ſpeaking evill, and blaſpheming the things they know not, as <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith verſe 10. And being by their corrupt light of nature, naturally born ſubtle ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters againſt the light of grace and faith: hereby out of the ſweet flowers where the Bee ſucketh honey, they by the cunning art of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice do ſuck poyſon: And then caſt the imputation thereof upon the truth with out-cries of errours, hereſies, and blaſphemies; when all the hereſie, and blaſphemie is the unbeliefe in their own hearts. And thus being thoſe <hi>truth-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62458:42"/> dogs</hi> (mentioned in the Scripture, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 2.) that bark in the day-time at true men, they ſtick not to charge the truth, that it breaketh the peace of the Church, and troubleth all <hi>Iſrael:</hi> when it is not he (as Gods word and the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed doctrine of our Church largely teach) that maintaineth the truth, and <hi>holdeth faſt the faithfull word, Tit.</hi> 1. 9. But the unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in the dead faith, that cavill and ſophiſtrate, and reſiſt the truth. Theſe are they that trouble the Church, that is, make tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults; becauſe they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62458:43"/> with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> leave wrangling, tumultuating; deriding, and ſcoffing at the truth of Chriſts myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as ſeeming errour, and fooliſhneſſe unto them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their falſe, bloody, holy zeal of Gods glory proceed to the laſt marke of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, even <hi>to ſmite Micai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah on the cheek,</hi> ſaying, <hi>When went the Spirit of the Lord from me to ſpeake unto thee? 1 King.</hi> 22. 24. And ſo they run with ſpeed to bitter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, and bloody perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, except they be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> truely enlightened and converted to the true faith,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62458:43"/> or this ſeed of the ſerpent be for nibling at the heels of Gods faithfull children, of God cruſhed in the head by the wiſe and godly Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or (as <hi>Cains</hi> brood) be caſt out of the houſe and Church of God as <hi>Iſmae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> and ſo cut off by God himſelf, as he ſaith <hi>Gal. 4. 30 Cast out the bond-woman and her ſonne, for the ſonne of the bond-woman ſhall not be heire with the ſonne of the free wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> And then and not till then they ceaſe to trouble the Church; God at the laſt thus plainly manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to the world, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their foreſaid holy,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62458:44"/> and bloody blind zeale of Gods glory ſeem very beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and be highly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before men, and in their own account; yet that it is moſt vile, and horrible abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in the ſight of God; as Chriſt himſelf te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth of ſuch, ſaying, <hi>ye are they that juſtifie your ſelves before men; but God knoweth your hearts: For that which is highly esteemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, is abomination in the ſight of God,</hi> Luk. 16. 15.</p>
            <p>All this deſcription and diſcovery of this dead faith, gilt over with the blind zeal and confidence of an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall obedience to all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62458:44"/> Gods commandements, is as pithily as briefly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the eſtabliſhed do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our Church, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus; That ſuch men as make a goodly ſhew of all good works, and many holy and godly ordinances, whereby they appear to the world the moſt religious and holy of all men: yet being blind and void of true juſtifying faith, that onely makes the inſide of the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell clean and pure, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 9 Chriſt that ſaw their hearts knew that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the ſight of God moſt unholy, moſt abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and fartheſt from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62458:45"/> God of all men. Againſt which Sects and their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended holineſſe, Chriſt cryeth out more vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than he did againſt any other perſons. But why are ſuch holy and godly men ſo abominable before God? <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed doctrine of our Church) although they ſeeme to the world moſt perfect men (marke I pray) <hi>both</hi> in life and doctrine, (why, what can be wiſhed more?) yet is their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prepoſterous, their doctrine ſowre leaven, and their life hypocriſie. <hi>Serm. of mans miſery. Sermon of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62458:45"/> free Iuſtification:</hi> and <hi>Sermon of good works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much of the markes to diſcerne who be in this dead faith; which as none can diſcern and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, but he that is in the true faith: becauſe ſuch an one onely hath the <hi>mind of Chriſt, by which he diſcerneth all things: but is judged of no man, 1 Cor.</hi> 2. 15, 16. So is the matter, ſo weighty and worthy to bee diſcovered, that I heartily wiſh that ſome man of a farre greater meaſure and gift of faith than my ſelf, would ſo point out and plainly lay forth the vileneſſe of the ſame, as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62458:46"/> that the uglineſſe of it might appear unto all men, as it is in it ſelf; yea I wiſh that every Chriſtian were a Preacher and writer againſt this moſt dangerous dead faith.</p>
            <p>3. Now thirdly, <hi>on the contrary ſide, Becauſe</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria inter ſe oppoſit a magis elucent; that is, <hi>Contraries ſet one against another, doe ſhine forth the brighter. Let us therefore conſider the parts likewiſe, of the true, lively, and ſaving faith, which are theſe three.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the true, humble, ſpirituall knowledge: for the true knowledge is an
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62458:46"/> humble knowledge, feeling (through a true ſight, yet but a weak ſight) the things of the kingdome of heaven, being ever ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to learne further and more even of our inferiours that bring the true word of God, and pure Goſpel of Chriſt, to the further edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us in our moſt holy faith, <hi>Iude 20. As learned A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos that was mighty in the Scriptures,</hi> being a zealous preacher was willing to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit conference with <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Preſcilla</hi> a woman, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>inſtructed by them in the way of the Lord more perfectly,</hi> hee preached Chriſt with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62458:47"/> great efficacy, <hi>Act. 18. 24. to</hi> 28. Yea this true humble knowledge is ever crying out with <hi>David, O open mine eyes that I may ſee the wonders of thy Law, Pſal.</hi> 119. 18. For which cauſe <hi>Paul</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fervently for the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, and all other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans whom hee had conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>That God the father of glory, would give unto them the ſpirit of wiſedome and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation in the knowledge of him, that the eye of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding might bee more enlightned, that they might know what the hope is of their calling, and what the riches of his glorious inheritance is in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62458:47"/> his Saints, Epheſ.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Againe, as the former blind and proud knowledge is but literall, ſo this true knowledge is ſpirituall, which by the ſpirit diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and ſeeth the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things of God, both of the Law and of the Goſpel, eſpecially diſcerning and ſeeing the inviſible benefits. and unſearchable riches of the Goſpel wrought upon us by the blood, death, and reſurrection of Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they are ſpoken <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 18. being impoſſible to humane reaſon, bodily ſight, ſenſe, and feeling, as theſe and ſuch like Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62458:48"/> teach. <hi>The eye hath not ſeen, nor the eares heard, nor hath entred in the heart of man,</hi> that is, the naturall man, <hi>the things that God hath prepared for them that love him. But God hath revealed them unto us by his ſpirit. For the ſpirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deepe things of God. For what man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a man that is in him? Even ſo the things of God knoweth no man, ſave the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. Now we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not the ſpirit of the world, but the ſpirit which is of God; that we might know,</hi> or as the originall word
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62458:48"/> is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>wee might ſee the things that are freely given to us of God, 1 Cor.</hi> 2. 9. to 13. But contrariwiſe, <hi>the naturall or the man</hi> of the meere humane ſoul, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not, or <hi>perceiveth not,</hi> or approveth not <hi>the things of the ſpirit of God,</hi> as they are ſpoken by the ſpirit, <hi>For they are fooliſhneſſe unto him, neither can he know them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſpiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; but he that is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, diſcerneth all things,</hi> verſ. 14, 15. Againe, hereupon did <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>Yea, doubtleſſe I count all things but loſſe, for the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62458:49"/> for whom I have ſuffered the loſse of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may gain Chriſt, that I may be found in him not having mine owne righteouſneſſe which is of the Law, but that which is by the faith of Chriſt, even that which is of God through faith,</hi> Phil. 3. 8, 9. Thus the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man diſcerneth, ſeeth, and onely eſteemeth and highly prizeth onely ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, and inviſible to the bodily eyes: and ſo hath an eare to heare what the ſpirit ſaith, whereof the Lord Chriſt ſo often ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, ſaying, <hi>Hee that hath eares to heare let him heare,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62458:49"/> Matth.</hi> 13. 9. and that which is often repeated, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. &amp; 3. chapters, ſaying, <hi>He that hath an eare let him heare what the ſpirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi> And theſe and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe doe <hi>compare ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things with ſpirituall, 1 Cor.</hi> 2. 13. And thus much of the true ſpirituall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hereof ariſeth the true lively and juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, which truly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us, conſiſting in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts perfect holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, making us ſo perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy and righteous,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62458:50"/> from all ſpot of ſinne in the ſight of God freely by faith onely, without works, that we feel true comfort, peace with God in our hearts, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt, as theſe and ſuch like Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teach: <hi>Eſa. 61. 10. I will greatly rejoyce in the Lord, and my ſoul ſhall bee joyfull in my God:</hi> why? what is the matter? what is the cauſe of ſuch joy and great rejoycing? why, <hi>Hee hath cloathed me with the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſalvation:</hi> That is juſt matter indeed of great joy: A man can wiſh no greater matter of joy, than to be cloathed with the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62458:50"/> of ſalvation: what is that garment of ſalvation? why, <hi>he hath covered me with the robes of righteouſneſſe, as a Bridegroome decketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his ornaments, and as a Bride adorneth her ſelf with her jewels.</hi> But the feaſt of the Goſpel being <hi>furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with gueſts both good and bad, the King came in to ſee the gueſts; and ſaw there a man that had not on this wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment: And hee ſaid unto him, Friend, how cameſt thou hither, and hast not on the wedding garment? and he was ſpeechleſſe: Then ſaid the King to the ſervants, Bind him hand and foot, take him
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62458:51"/> away, and cast him into utter darkneſse, there ſhall be weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing of teeth, Matth. 22. 10. to</hi> 14. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore get on the <hi>white robe that thou maist bee cloathed, and thy filthy nakedneſſe doe not appeare: Anoint thine eyes with eye-ſalve, that thou maist ſee,</hi> Rev. 3. 18. <hi>For all have ſinned, and are deprived of the glory of God: but are juſtified</hi> (that is, made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous againe) <hi>freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus, Rom. 3. 23, 24. For as by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners: ſo by the obedience of one ſhall many</hi> (to the end of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62458:51"/> the world) <hi>be made righteous,</hi> Rom. 5. 19. <hi>That as ſin hath reigned unto death, even ſo might grace reigne by righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſse unto eternall life by Ieſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> ver. 21. <hi>Therefore being justified by faith, we have peace with God, Rom.</hi> 5. 1. And thus we are regenerated and freely made new creatures to Godward, whereby we are made all new, even the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God in this faith of Chriſt: as <hi>Paul</hi> in ſpirit teſtified, ſaying, <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature: old things are paſſed away, Behold all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new:</hi> and all things are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62458:52"/> of God who hath reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us unto himſelf by Jeſus Chriſt. But how are all things become new? why, <hi>God hath made him to be ſin for us, who knew no ſin:</hi> to what end? <hi>that we might be made the righteouſneſse of God in him,</hi> that is, by this faith in him.</p>
            <p>Thus are we become all new, and ſo by relying and reſting wholly and onely in theſe inviſible riches wrought upon us by the blood of Chriſt, impoſſible to our reaſon, and contrary to our bodily ſight, ſenſe and feeling, we do ſo walke in the ſteps of the faith of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62458:52"/> our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> as they are (that we may not erre, wander, and go aſtray from them) plainly deſcribed by <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 4. 19. to 25. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And he not weak in faith conſidered not his owne body now dead, being almoſt an hundred yeares old: nor yet the deadneſſe of Sarahs womb, neither did hee doubt of the promiſe of God</hi> (concerning the juſtifying ſeed) <hi>through unbelief: But was ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in faith, and gave glory to God, being fully aſſured, that hee which had promiſed</hi> (would bee as good as his word, though it ſeemed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo impoſſible to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62458:53"/> ſent ſenſe and feeling) <hi>and was able to do it.</hi> And it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe. <hi>Now it was not written for Abrahams ſake onely, that it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe: but alſo for us to whom it ſhall bee imputed for righteouſneſse, which beleeve in him that raiſed up Ieſus our Lord from the dead, who was delivered to death for our ſinnes,</hi> to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end than <hi>to aboliſh them</hi> from before his father, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 26. whereby <hi>the blood of Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God doth make us clean from all ſinne,</hi> 1 Iohn 1. 7. <hi>And is riſen againe for our full
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62458:53"/> and perfect juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the true lively and juſtifying faith: This faith makes us not baſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly children, but the true, kind, proper, and naturall children, not of <hi>Abram</hi> but of <hi>Abraham.</hi> This is the faith by which we are truly <hi>bleſsed,</hi> and as truly ſaved as <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf; as <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 8. 9. ſaying <hi>The Scriptures</hi> (that is, the ſpirit of God ſpeaking in <hi>the Scriptures) foreſeeing that God would juſtifie the Heathen through faith, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the joyfull newes unto Abraham, ſaying, In thee ſhall all the Gentiles be bleſſed: So
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62458:54"/> that they which be of this faith, are bleſſed with faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Abraham.</hi> And what can we deſire more than to be bleſſed? Now becauſe this free juſtification, or the having on this wedding garment, cannot be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and enjoyed by this ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith, but by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the gaping wounds of Chriſt, bleeding out his blood and life to effect this free juſtification upon the beleever. Therefore onely this juſtifying faith ſmites the heart of the beleever with the true love of Chriſt and of God in Chriſt, which reflecteth back from
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62458:54"/> God generally upon all men, as they bear the image of God, yet reſteth princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally upon the Church and houſhold of faith, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the true beleevers to abound in every good work, <hi>doing good unto all men, but eſpecially unto the houſhold of faith,</hi> Gal. 6. 10. and that not of conſtraint, corruptly, and hypocritically; but cheerfully, ſincerely, and ioyfully: becauſe both Chriſt and <hi>the Kingdome of God,</hi> and the Kingdome of heaven by this true, lively, iuſtifying faith <hi>is within us, Luke</hi> 17. 21. Into which Kingdome of heaven <hi>no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62458:55"/> thing can enter, Rev.</hi> 21. 27. Becauſe this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven <hi>is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and peace, and ioy in the holy Ghost,</hi> Rom. 14. 17. And the more this faith of free Juſtification, and of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on this wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, encreaſeth; the more this peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt encreaſeth. For the which it is called <hi>the garment of ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Eſa.</hi> 61. 3. And the more this peace and joy encreaſeth, the more the foreſaid love encreaſeth, and enflameth the heart to walk freely, cheerfully, and zealouſly in all Gods will
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62458:55"/> and commandements de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratively to manward, and to doe our vocatious, and all good workes freely, of meere love, without hope of reward or fear of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is true ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, which cauſeth us to live here among men, as Chriſt himſelfe lived, that is, not onely doing all things, but alſo cheerfully ſuffering all things to edifie one another in our moſt holy faith that onely ſaves us, <hi>Iude</hi> 20. And to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God our reconciled and well pleaſed father in Chriſt, as St. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. Epiſt. chap. 2. verſ. 6. teſtifieth,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62458:56"/> ſaying, <hi>He that ſaith he abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in Chriſt, ought even ſo to walke as hee hath walked.</hi> Thus much of the true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of this juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith that worketh by love, there followes inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably a true right Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call zeale of Gods glory, whereby we feeling how by our originall corruption, and by breaking the tenth commandement, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the firſt commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all the reſt in our beſt good works, whereby that ſaying of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> is true in our beſt good works, That <hi>whoſoever ſhall keep the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62458:56"/> whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all:</hi> we finde both <hi>our ſelves</hi> and all our works and beſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>to be</hi> ſo <hi>ſhut up under ſin, Gal.</hi> 3. 22. that being truly humbled with a vile eſteem of our ſelves and all our beſt good works, we do grant not with lip and tongue only (as many ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard Proteſtants do) but do feele in our hearts in deed and truth, <hi>that all our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſse,</hi> even of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>is as</hi> foule, ſtained, <hi>filthy rags, Eſay</hi> 64. 6. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our hearts are ſo infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſuch an high pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and onely eſteeming
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62458:57"/> of the wedding garment of Chriſts obedience and righteouſneſſe perfectly iuſtifying us, and all our works. That not onely every true Miniſter of the Goſpel, but alſo every true Chriſtian ceaſeth all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention about works, and is carried with a zealous affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>to know nothing among Gods people ſave Ieſus Chriſt and him crucified</hi> to iuſtifie them, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 2. by which they are made ſuch true bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning coals of Gods Altar, ſo enflamed with this holy fire of Chriſts love from heaven, that they cannot chuſe but enflame and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62458:57"/> kindle all others that come neare them, caring for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to be found our ſelves, and to cauſe others to be found in Chriſt, that is, not having our owne righteouſneſſe in eſteeme, which at the beſt is but mans glory before men on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 2. but in the moſt precious robes of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, making both us, and all our workes perfectly holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous from all ſpot of ſin in Gods ſight, freely by faith onely without workes; and ſo do truely know Chriſt, and grace, and faith, and works rightly, as theſe and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62458:58"/> ſuch like Scriptures teach: <hi>Yea doubtleſſe, I count all things but loſſe for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent knowledge ſake of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win or gain Christ, and bee found in him, not having mine owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, even the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is of God through faith,</hi> Phil. 3. 8, 9. neither <hi>doe I paſſe of croſſes and afflictions at all, nor doe I count my life deare unto my ſelfe, ſo that I may fulfill my courſe with ioy, and the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62458:58"/> which I have received of the Lord Ieſus, to teſtifie the Goſpel</hi> (that is, the ioyfull newes) <hi>of the grace of God,</hi> Act. 20. 24. <hi>That I might be the Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt toward the Gentiles, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring</hi> (as the worſhip of God) <hi>the Goſpell</hi> (that is, the ioyfull newes) <hi>of God: That the offering up of the Gentiles might be acceptable being ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> So that from <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and round about unto Illiricum I have</hi> (by Chriſt working in me) <hi>cauſed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound the Goſpel</hi> (that is, the ioyfull newes) <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 15. 16, 19. <hi>Yea ſo I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62458:59"/> my ſelf to preach this ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full newes, not where Chriſt was named, leſt I ſhould build upon another mans foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But as it is written, to whom hee was not ſpoken of, they ſhall ſee, and they that have not heard, they ſhall understand,</hi> verſ. 20, 21.</p>
            <p>All which againe is as briefly as notably expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>by the eſtabliſhed Doctrine of our Church, out of Saint</hi> Baſil, ſaying thus, <hi>This is a perfect and whole reioycing in God, when a man advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not himſelfe for his owne righteouſneſſe: but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth himſelfe to lack true
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62458:59"/> iuſtice and righteouſneſſe; and to be iuſtified by onely faith in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he doth glory; in what? in the contempt of his own righteouſneſſe; and that he looketh for the righteouſneſſe of God by faith, <hi>Sermon of ſalvation ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part.</hi> Which <hi>eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed doctrine of our Church is lamentably loſt</hi> of too many Profeſſors among us now a dayes. In ſtead whereof muſt needs come in the contrary doctrine, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of reioycing in and greatly eſteeming our owne righteouſneſſe: but of ſmall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62458:60"/> ioy and little regarding of Chriſts righteouſneſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly iuſtifying us. Thus much of the right zeale of God.</p>
            <p>4. The fourth and laſt point, and main thing to be conſidered concerning this dead faith, is; What is the ſpeedieſt courſe and moſt effectuall meanes by which wee may come out of this dead faith, into the true live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and iuſtifying faith, and by which we may call others out of the ſame; which ſpeedieſt courſe or moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall meanes, conſiſteth but in two maine things throughly marked and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62458:60"/> deeply conſidered.</p>
            <p>1. The firſt is to look ſo truely into the pure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite righteous nature of God, that we cleerly ſee in the two looking-glaſſes, both of the Law and of the Goſpel, the horrible fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of ſinne to be ſuch, that God cannot but curſe and throw out of his favour and liking the creature that hath any ſinne in his ſight, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Deut. 27. 26. Curſed is every man that continueth not in all things that are written in the booke of the Law to do them:</hi> Mark, <hi>Curſed</hi> (that is, caſt out of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62458:61"/> my love and favour for ever. (<hi>Go ye curſed into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire,</hi> Matth. 25. 41.) <hi>is every one that continueth not in all things,</hi> that is, that hath the leaſt ſinne in his ſight. For if we have the leaſt ſinne in Gods ſight, wee doe not continue in all things, and ſo muſt needs be accurſed of God; or elſe his righteous nature muſt needs be changeable in his definitive ſentence againſt ſinne, which cannot bee. Fearfull examples hereof are, Firſt, the Angels, who although they were moſt glorious creatures for pure holineſſe and righteouſnes:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62458:61"/> yet as ſoone as they concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but one ſinne, but in thought onely, <hi>God ſpared them not</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) that ſinned, but caſt them down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, and delivered them into chaines of darkneſſe to be reſerved unto condemnation, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 4. Another fearfull example is that of <hi>Adam,</hi> who by one ſinne onely brought upon him by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, did caſt himſelf into death and deſtruction, and all his poſterity, even infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite millions of men and women into infinite milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſins and miſeries, as <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. ſaying, <hi>As by one man ſin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62458:62"/> into the world, and by ſin death: ſo death goeth over all men, in that all have ſinned, whereby through the offenſe of one many bee dead,</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>Becauſe the iudgement came by that one offenſe upon all men to condemnation,</hi> verſe 16. Now the reaſon why God cannot but curſe and caſt away out of his love and favour, the creature that hath any ſinne in Gods ſight, is becauſe the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble filthineſſe of ſinne is ſuch to Gods infinite pure and righteous nature, that God cannot but deteſt, hate, abhorre, and count abominable the creature in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62458:62"/> whom he ſeeth any ſinne, or that hath the leaſt ſin in his ſight, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach. <hi>Behold the heavens are unclean in Gods ſight, how much more is man filthy and abominable, who drinketh iniquity like water? Iob</hi> 15. 15, 16. Thus we ſee that ſinne doth make the creature ſpiritually foule, filthy, loathſome, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in Gods ſight, though no curſe or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould follow upon the ſame: as Chriſt himſelf alſo teſtifieth <hi>Mark 7. 20. to</hi> 23. ſaying, <hi>That which commeth out of the man, that defileth the man. For out of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62458:63"/> the heart of man come evill thoughts, adulteries, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, murders, thefts, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, wickedneſse, deceit, laſciviouſneſſe, an evill eye, blaſphemies, pride, fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> All theſe evill things <hi>come from within, and theſe defile a man.</hi> Therefore did the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> ſay, <hi>God is of pure eyes and cannot ſee ſinne, and cannot behold iniquity;</hi> but he muſt needs deſtroy either the ſinne or the ſinner from before him. <hi>But for this purpoſe was the ſonne of God made manifeſt that</hi> (in the faithfull) <hi>hee might deſtroy ſinne, the worke of the Devill,</hi> 1 John 3. 6.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62458:63"/> Becauſe <hi>he was</hi> made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to take away our ſinnes. For in him is no ſin, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. But unto the unbeleeving Jewes the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lords hand is not ſhortned that it cannot ſave, neither is his eare heavie that it cannot heare: but your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities have ſeparated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you and your God, and your ſinnes have hindred good things from you,</hi> Eſay 29. 1. Jer. 5. 25.</p>
            <p>And for the deeper ſight of this evill of ſinne, hear three things which the Law teacheth concerning ſinne, and deeply to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and daily, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62458:64"/> to be preſſed upon ſecure conſciences.</p>
            <p>As firſt, The horrible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the evill of ſinne, becauſe the leaſt ſinne by the Law forbidding it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19, &amp; 20. chapters, in fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thundring, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and terrible earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, &amp; flaming fire reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to the midſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Hereby the leaſt ſin (I ſay) is made out of meaſure ſinfull: Becauſe the leaſt ſin is encreaſed to diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and diſobedience is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; that is, ſpirituall high treaſon againſt the higheſt Majeſty; as <hi>Samuel</hi> teſtifies of the diſobedience
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62458:64"/> of King <hi>Saul, 1 Sam.</hi> 15. 23. And as the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> confeſſeth of his ſinnes, and the ſinnes of his people, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>We have ſinned, and done wickedly, yea, we have rebelled even by departing from thy precepts; and thus</hi> (ſaith hee againe) <hi>have wee rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God,</hi> Dan. 9. 5, 9. <hi>But rebellion</hi> (ſaith <hi>Samuel) is as the ſinne of witchcraft, and tranſgreſsion is ſtubbornneſſe, and ſtubbornneſſe is wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and idolatry. Thus did the Law enter upon ſinne, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the offenſe thereof to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound,</hi> Rom. 5. 20. And thus the leaſt ſinne by the Commandement forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62458:65"/> it in ſuch terrible thundring and lightning, becomes out of meaſure, or exceeding ſinfull, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 13. And this is the firſt thing that the Law teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth concerning ſin.</p>
            <p>2. The ſecond thing which the Law teacheth is the multitude of our ſinnes, that the moſt honeſt and moſt religious among us are guilty of, againſt every one of the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: eſpecially by the ſpirituall breach of the Law, as Chriſt expoundeth the ſame in the fifth, ſixth, and ſeventh chapters of <hi>Matthew,</hi> which made <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:62458:65"/> to ſee that his whole nature was nothing elſe but a meer contrariety to the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all meaning of the Law, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>The Law is ſpirituall, but I am carnall, ſold under ſin, Rom.</hi> 7. 14. And which made <hi>David</hi> to cry out ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>My ſinnes have taken ſuch hold upon me, that I am not able to look up: yea, they are mee in number than the haires of my head, Therefore my heart hath failed me,</hi> Pſal. 40. 12.</p>
            <p>3. The third thing that the Law teacheth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſinne, is the fivefold puniſhment belonging to the leaſt ſinne: which God
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62458:66"/> executeth daily and hourly upon one another, being Gods whip of five ſtrings, with which he laſheth the children of men in one place or other daily and continually, which are theſe five.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, the curſe of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 15. to 20. <hi>If thou wilt not hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God</hi> (namely which he ſpake in thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and lightning, and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire) <hi>but dost break his commandments,</hi> (that is, doſt do the leaſt ſin) <hi>then all theſe curſes ſhall come upon thee, and overtake thee: curſed ſhalt thou be in the town, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62458:66"/> curſed in the field; curſed ſhall bee thy basket and thy ſtore,</hi> (that is, thy abundance that ſeemes to thee a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſhall be to thee accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:) <hi>curſed ſhall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy land, and the encreaſe of thy kine, and the flocks of thy ſheep: curſed ſhalt thou bee when thou comeſt in, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alſo when thou goest out. The Lord ſhall ſend upon thee curſing, vexation, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all that thou ſetteſt thy hand to do, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The ſecond puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is hardneſſe of heart, that is, no ſpirituall ſenſe or feeling, but little caring for
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62458:67"/> this curſe of God upon us for ſin, and a ſleight regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of free juſtification, which is the onely remedy and means that ſhould heal us of this ſinne and curſe, <hi>Matth. 13. 15. For this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples heart is waxed groſſe, and their ears are dull of hearing, and with their eyes they have winked, leſt they ſhould ſee with their eyes, and heare with their eares, and ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand with their hearts, and ſhould bee converted, and I ſhould heale them: But my people would not heare my voice, nor Iſrael would none of me: So I gave them up to the hardneſſe of their hearts, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:62458:67"/> they have walked in their own counſell,</hi> Pſal. 81. 11, 12. whereby <hi>thou after thy hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and impenitent heart heapeſt up like a treaſure to thy ſelfe, wrath againſt the day of wrath, and of the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the juſt judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2. 5.</p>
            <p>3. The third ſort of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſinne, is all manner of miſeries, croſſes, and afflictions to body, goods, and name, which are ready every moment to ſtrike us: but to what end? to knock for us, and give us warning to be ſure that we bee freely juſtified, and have on the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62458:68"/> of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>Iob</hi> 33. 19. to verſe 26. <hi>A man is chaſtened with pain upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with ſtrong paine, ſo that his life abhorreth bread, and his ſoul dainty meats. His fleſh is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed away; and his bones, that were not ſeen, ſtick out: his life draweth neare to the grave,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>if there be a meſſenger with him, an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter one of a thouſand, to ſhew unto a man his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> that is, his juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſneſſe by Chriſt, <hi>then God is gracious unto him, and ſaith, deliver
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62458:68"/> him from going down into the pit, I have found a ranſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. The fourth puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne is, that uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain death is ready every moment to ſtrike us, wee knowing neither the time when, nor the place where, nor the manner how death will ſtrike us: as God himſelf ſaith, <hi>Deut. 28. 66. If thou breakeſt my Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> and ſo doſt ſin, <hi>thy life ſhall hang in doubt before thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt have juſt cauſe to feare both night and day: for thou ſhalt have no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of thy life:</hi> For God ſaid to the rich man, <hi>Luke 12. 20. Thou fool, this night
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62458:69"/> will they</hi> (that is, the devils) <hi>fetch away thy ſoule from thee, and then whoſe ſhall theſe things bee which thou haſt provided. So is every man that is not rich in God,</hi> that is, which hath not on the wedding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which only maketh us rich in God, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. 18.</p>
            <p>5 The fifth and laſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſinne is, when death, which is ſo uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, is come; then follows the full execution of Gods juſtice in hell fire, there to endure eaſleſſe and endleſſe torments for ever and ever. Therefore ſaith Chriſt the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62458:69"/> Teacher of true wiſedome, <hi>I ſay unto you, my friends, be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that are not able to doe any more: But I will forewarne you whom you ſhall feare: Feare him which after he hath killed, hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alſo to caſt into hell; yea I ſay unto you, feare him, Luke</hi> 12. 4, 5. for then he ſhall ſay, <hi>Depart yee curſed</hi> (which all are that are not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) <hi>into everlaſting fire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the devill and his angels: and theſe ſhall goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into everlaſting paine: but the righteous only,</hi> that is, only they that are made perfectly holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62458:70"/> in the ſight of God freely with Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <hi>ſhall goe into life everlaſting, Mat.</hi> 25. 41, 46.</p>
            <p>Thus ought theſe three maine things that the Law teacheth concerning ſin to be daily and diligently preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon ſleeping conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſecure in the leaſt ſin; untill the moſt upright, honeſt, yea, and moſt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified man in works may feele himſelfe ſlaine by the <hi>Law,</hi> eſpecially by the tenth Commandement, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9. ſaying, <hi>For I once was alive without the Law; but when the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,</hi> thou ſhalt not luſt,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62458:70"/> or covet, that is, thou ſhalt not have the leaſt motion to any ſinne, <hi>came,</hi> that I underſtood it, <hi>ſinne revived,</hi> that is, I ſaw my beſt good works to be ſinne which I took to be no ſinne before; <hi>but I died,</hi> that is, I ſaw my ſelfe loſt and damned by that beautifull ſinne, which I took to be a good work before God, and no ſinne. <hi>And the ſame Commandment which was</hi> by obeying it <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained unto life, I found</hi> by breaking it in my beſt good works <hi>to be unto death. For ſinne,</hi> that is, originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption dwelling in me, <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king occaſion</hi> or force <hi>by the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62458:71"/> commandement, deceived me,</hi> that is, made my beſt good works (as I did them) ſinne, when I took them to be no ſinne, <hi>and by it,</hi> that is, by the commandement diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed and broken, <hi>ſlew me,</hi> that is, made me to ſee, and feele my ſelfe to be in my beſt, and moſt ſanctified good works, a loſt and damned creature: <hi>Becauſe ſinne,</hi> that is originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption dwelling in me, <hi>that it might appeare ſinne, did work death in me by that which is good,</hi> that is, by that tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that into ſinne by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which was done by the good and holy Law of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:62458:71"/> God, <hi>that ſinne by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement</hi> diſobeyed <hi>might become</hi> out of meaſure or <hi>exceeding ſinfull.</hi> Hereupon and for this cauſe doth the moſt ſanctified childe of God truly enlightened, and ſlaine by the Law, by this right underſtanding of this tenth commandement, ſee and feele that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 3. 9. to 19. to be moſt true in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and in his beſt ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied works, namely, That <hi>there is none righteous no not one, there is none that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth, there is none that ſeeketh God; they are all gone out of the way, they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:62458:72"/> become abominable, and unprofitable. There is none that doth good no not one. Their throat is an open ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, with their tongues they have uſed deceit, the poyſon of Aſps is under their lips, whoſe mouth is full of curſing and bitterneſſe, their feet are ſwift,</hi> by anger and malice, <hi>to ſhed blood; deſtruction and miſery are in their wayes, and the way of peace they have not knowne; there is no feare of God before their eyes.</hi> And whereas the naturall man in the dead faith will by his civill, honeſt, and ſuppoſed ſanctified life, put all this away from himſelfe to ſuch
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:62458:72"/> as are profane and groſly wicked; ſaying, that this is ſpoken of them that are meerly and wholly in the eſtate of nature, and that ſo peradventure he might have been ſuch a one, but now (thanks be unto God) he is not ſuch a one; yet the true ſanctified children of God, that are truly enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſee the ſpirituall meaning of the Law, doe grant and truly feele, that by their daily and continuall ſpirituall breaches of the <hi>Law,</hi> they are truly ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as <hi>Paul</hi> here deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth; ſo ſhut up under ſin, both they and all their beſt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62458:73"/> ſanctified good works, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 22. that <hi>there is not one that doth good, no not one.</hi> Whereby they feele <hi>that every mouth,</hi> even of the moſt ſanctified, <hi>is ſtopped, and all the world is found ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the judgement of God.</hi> A cleare example of the truth hereof is <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who although he was one of the moſt ſanctified amongſt men; yet he cried out, ſaying, <hi>The Law is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, but I am carnall, ſold under ſinne: for to will is preſent with me; but I finde no meanes how to performe that which is good, Rom.</hi> 7. 18. And thus feeling in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:62458:73"/> himſelfe with the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> that all his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſanctification was as foule, menſtrous, filthy rags, <hi>Eſay</hi> 64. 6. becauſe in all his good works he brake the tenth Commandement, and ſo as much as lay in him, did deſtroy himſelfe in all his good works, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13. 9. Even death it ſelfe being in the pot of his moſt ſanctified good works and beſt actions; therefore hee cried out, <hi>O miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me from the body of this death! Rom.</hi> 7. 24. This is to bee ſlaine by the Law, this is to underſtand the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:62458:74"/> Law rightly, eſpecially the tenth Commandement. And this is the firſt means to come out of this dead faith, and to call others out of the ſame, being through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marked and deeply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            <p>2 The ſecond meanes to come out of this dead faith, and to call others out of the ſame is, truly to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and open unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the excellency of free juſtification: That as the ſpirit hath convinced us, and all our beſt works of ſinne by the looking-glaſſe of the Law, ſo the ſpirit may alſo convince us of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62458:74"/> free given righteouſneſſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 8, 9, 10. namely, that wee and all our works are of unjuſt made juſt, that is, perfeſtly holy and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous from all ſpot of ſin in the ſight of God freely by faith only without works. And mark how I ſay, not ſimply <hi>free juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> but the excellency of free Juſtification muſt be diligently looked into, and deeply conſidered in foure principall reſpects.</p>
            <p>1 Firſt, in the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and glorious cauſes of it, being the glorious work of the whole God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head wherein God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:62458:75"/> in giving his ſonne, and God the ſonne in pouring forth his blood and life, and God the holy Ghoſt in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying it to us, and in cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, though myſtically, yet truly, our ſouls and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with this wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in creating the new eyes of faith to ſee theſe ſpirituall riches, doe all work ſeverally and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully to effect the ſame upon us, and that alſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, onely by free grace, that is, God reſpectign no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or worthineſſe in us to deſerve the ſame, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that we feele our wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched miſery: nor reſpecting
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62458:75"/> no evils or unworthineſſe in us to hinder the free ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his rich grace: <hi>That it might be to the praiſe of the glory of his free grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee hath made us freely accepted in his beloved one, Eph.</hi> 1. 6. And for this cauſe doth God beſtow this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit upon us, that is, upon the young children of Chriſtian parents, uſually and ordinarily in our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, even when wee were little Infants; God pitying our miſery when we could not pitty our ſelves, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed us from the ſpirituall blood of our originall ſinne, <hi>Ezek. 16. 6, 9. with the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62458:76"/> of the new birth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the holy Ghost, that we being iuſtified by his grace ſhould be made heires of eternall life,</hi> Tit. 3. 5, 6, 7. <hi>And <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, having made us pure and clean by the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of water through the word. That hee might</hi> (even when wee were little ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Infants, and thereby as good as double dead to all ſenſe and feeling in treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſinnes, and by nature the children of wrath) <hi>make us to himſelfe a glorious Church, not having</hi> now at this preſent time (as the Greeke and Latine partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſignifie) <hi>one ſpot or
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62458:76"/> wrinkle of ſinne or any ſuch thing, but are holy and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame, Epheſ.</hi> 5. 26, 27. Becauſe wee are made thus perfectly pure and clean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, not onely from that one offenſe of our ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne, but alſo from all the many actuall ſinnes of our whole life, even in our baptiſme, even when we are Infants, that is, utterly helpleſſe in our ſelves, that all this bleſſedneſſe may be the more freely upon us: And that (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>Although the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was by one offenſe unto condemnation,</hi> yet the gift is not ſo; <hi>but the free gift is of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62458:77"/> many offenſes to iuſtification,</hi> Rom. 5. 16. <hi>So that if by one mans offenſe death reigned by one, much more they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that abundance of grace, and of the gift of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall reigne in life by one,</hi> that is, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> verſ. 17. And thus wee ſee, that as there is no difference of young or old, but all have ſinned, and are deprived, and come ſhort of the glory of God: ſo all that receive this free gift of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, are juſtified freely by Gods grace through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that is in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23, 24. And thus much of the excellent
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62458:77"/> cauſes of free juſtification briefly touched.</p>
            <p>2. Secondly, wee muſt conſider deeply the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent nature it ſelf of free iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, in that it is the head and chiefeſt benefit of the Goſpel, whereby, by the power of Gods imputation we are ſo clothed with the wedding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that of uniuſt we are made iuſt before God, that is, ſo perfectly holy and righteous from all ſpot of ſinne in the ſight of God freely, by faith alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, That (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>wee are made the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:62458:78"/> righteouſneſſe of God in him,</hi> that is, in this faith in him: The excellency of which benefit was ſo rightly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſo diligently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that he thereupon breaketh out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe words of ioy and admiration of the ſame, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Qualis ſermo? what a ſaying is this? what heart or underſtanding can ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend it, or ſet it forth? For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the righteous one he made a ſinner, that hee might make the ſinners righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: nay he ſpeaketh not ſo ſleightly neither, but that which is farre more: For he ſaid not, hee made him a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:62458:78"/> but ſinne; that we might be made, he ſaith, not righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but righteouſneſſe; yea and the righteouſneſſe of God. For this is of God, becauſe it is not of workes: For the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer righteouſneſſe of good eſteem in the Church was the righteouſneſſe of the Law and of works; but this is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse of God. Becauſe it is neceſsary that no ſpot bee found in it, and from hence all ſinne vaniſheth away.</hi> Thus hee teacheth the magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence both of the gift and giver.</p>
            <p>3. Thirdly, to look the better into the nature of this benefit; we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:62458:79"/> deeply the excelent parts of this wonderfull benefit, which are theſe two chiefly.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, that this wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe doth (though myſtically, that is, above our reaſon, ſight, ſenſe, and feeling, that we may live by faith in the truth and power of God ſpeaking, and not by ſight, ſenſe, and feeling, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 18, to 25. yet freely) take away, and truly aboliſh, not out of our fleſh, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 8. but utterly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh from before God, and out of Gods ſight, all our ſinnes, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Iohn 1. 29. Behold the lambe of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:62458:79"/> God that taketh away the ſins of the world: For I,</hi> not you, but <hi>even I,</hi> being <hi>Sol iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> the ſhining ſunne of righteouſneſſe, <hi>Mal. 4. 2. will do away your iniquities like darkneſſe, and aboliſh your ſinnes like a miſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce ye heavens, for the Lord hath done it; Shout ye lower parts of the earth, break forth into praiſes, O mountaines. For thus hath the Lord redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Iacob, and thus will he be glorified in Iſrael,</hi> Eſa. 43. 25. and 44. 22, 23. For <hi>by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath Chriſt purified and made us cleane from our ſins, and is ſet at the right hand of the higheſt Maieſty,</hi> Heb. 1. 3 Becauſe <hi>if the blood of bulls
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:62458:80"/> and of goats, and the aſhes of an heifer, ſprinkling the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, ſanctifieth to the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the fleſh: How much more ſhall the blood of Chriſt, who through the eternall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit offered himſellfe without ſpot to God, purge, purifie,</hi> or make clean, <hi>our conſciences from dead workes to ſerve the living God,</hi> Heb. 9. 13, 14. Therefore <hi>did hee now once in the end of the world appear</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, to aboliſh, <hi>to doe away, or to put away ſinne, by the ſacrifice of himſelfe,</hi> Heb. 9. 26. <hi>For Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is that faithfull witneſſe, and that firſt begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the dead, and that
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:62458:80"/> Prince of the Kings of the earth, who hath loved us, and hath waſhed us from our ſins in his owne blood,</hi> Rev. 1. 5. whereby <hi>the blood of Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God doth make us cleane from all ſinne, 1 Ioh.</hi> 1. 7. Now the ſonne having thus aboliſhed our ſinnes from before God, or out of Gods ſight, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 22. Hereupon doth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pardon, remit, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give all the puniſhment and evill that is due to thoſe ſinnes, which his ſonne hath freely done away and truely aboliſhed out of his fathers ſight, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that teſtimony
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:62458:81"/> of <hi>David, Bleſſed is the man whoſe iniquities are forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and whoſe ſinnes are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, Pſal.</hi> 32. 1. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is all the anger of the father, and all his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, diſcontentment, death, and all other evils ceaſed, upon the juſtified perſon before God the father. And thus much briefly of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the firſt part of free juſtification.</p>
            <p>2. The excellency of the ſecond part of free juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is, That this wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe doth not only make us &amp; preſent us righteous in the ſight
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:62458:81"/> of God, but it alſo maketh us perfectly, and complete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſufficiently holy, and righteous from all ſpot of ſin in the ſight of God, freely by faith onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes, or without our perfect working; Yea, ſo ſufficiently, and complete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and perfectly holy, and righteous, that though my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically, yet whereſoever we ſit, or walk, we ſhine glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly holy, and righteous in the ſight of God, freely, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Rom. 5. 19. For as by one mans diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence many were made ſinners: ſo by the obedience of one man
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:62458:82"/> ſhall many be made righteous: whereby if by the offenſe of one, death reigned by one: much more, they which receive the abundance of grace, and that abundance of the gift of righteouſneſſe, ſhall reigne in life through one, even Ieſus Christ, Rom.</hi> 5. 17. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> propheſie to <hi>Daniel,</hi> that after ſeventy weeks of yeares, not onely ſinne ſhould be finiſhed, and tranſgreſſion made an end of, and reconciliation made for iniquity: <hi>but alſo everlasting righteouſneſse be brought in upon the faithfull, Dan.</hi> 9. 24. Thus is this
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:62458:82"/> righteouſneſſe called not only an abundance of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting righteouſneſſe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hence it is ſaid to make us complete before God, even <hi>complete in him which is the head of all principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, Col.</hi> 2. 10. Hence it is ſaid to make us perfect, as <hi>with one ſacrifice he hath made perfect for ever all them that are ſanctified, Heb.</hi> 10. 14. Hence it is ſaid to make us, and preſent us to God a glorious Church, as <hi>he hath made us pure or clean, by the waſhing of water through the word, to make us to himſelfe a glorious
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:62458:83"/> Church, not having,</hi> now at this preſent time, (as the Greek and Latine Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſignifie) <hi>one ſpot or wrinckle of ſinne, or any ſuch thing:</hi> but to bee ſo holy, <hi>that wee are unblameable,</hi> or without blemiſh, <hi>before God Eph.</hi> 27. Becauſe <hi>in the body of his fleſh through death he makes us,</hi> or preſents us, <hi>ſo holy that we are</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>without all blame, and without all fault in Gods ſight, if we continue rooted and grounded in this faith;</hi> upon which place <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>He hath not only freed us from ſin, but alſo he hath made us honourable,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:62458:83"/> and glorious in Gods ſight.</hi> Hence it is that this wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe was ſignified by the veſture of the gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the bride of Chriſt a Queen, and all glorious within, that is, ſpiritually, and myſtically, ſaying, <hi>At thy right hand doth ſtand the Queene in a veſture of the gold of Ophir, and ſhee is all glorious within, Pſalm</hi> 45. 9. Hence is the Church, and every true beleever, made that great wonder in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that is, under the time and ſtate of the Goſpel, called every where in the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:62458:84"/> New Teſtament <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, Matth.</hi> 11. 11, 12. and chapter 13. But what is this wonder? <hi>A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that is, in generall, the whole Church; but in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, every true beleeving ſoule, which is as truely by faith married to Chriſt, as any woman can be married to her husband, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 30. But what of this woman? <hi>Amicta ſole, cloathed with the ſunne</hi> that ſhineth in the firmament; that is, clothed with the glorious robes of Chriſts perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, making her, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe ſitteth or walketh, to ſhine as glorious in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:62458:84"/> Gods eyes, as the ſunne ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth glorious in our eyes, when ſhee ſhineth in her brighteſt hue. Thus hath Chriſt made his Church to himſelfe a glorious Church, <hi>Epheſ. 5. 27. And hath the moone under her feet,</hi> that is, the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Law directing the feet of her walking and converſation here before men, and ſhining by ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication declaratively to man-ward, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 16. as the moone ſhineth, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth light, that is, man walking in the dark night of this world: and yet hath this moone of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:62458:85"/> on under her feet, as of ſmall eſteeme, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the glorious ſunne of Chriſts perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, with which ſhe is clothed, <hi>Phil. 3. 8, 9. And hath a Crowne of twelve ſtars upon her head;</hi> that is, hath the doctrine of the Goſpel taught by the twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and all faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (likened to ſtars, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 16, 20.) in higheſt eſteem, as her chiefeſt ornament or crowne. And thus we ſee how <hi>Chriſt who knew no ſin, was made ſinne for us, that we might be made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse of God,</hi> by true faith <hi>in him, 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 21. And thus
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:62458:85"/> much bee briefly ſpoken of the excellency of the two parts of free iuſtification.</p>
            <p>4. Fourthly and laſtly, for the right underſtanding and powerfull laying forth of the excellency of free Juſtification, we muſt deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider, and diligently lay forth the excellent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and precious fruits of free Juſtification, which are briefly all needfull bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings both temporall and eternall; but chiefly and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially theſe ſixe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, that by this free Juſtification we are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, and ſo reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:62458:86"/> into his love and favour again: that all anger and diſpleaſure of God being ceaſed and aboliſhed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, God is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and at peace with us, as it was notably propheſied by the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>I will heale their backſlidings, and I will love them freely, for mine anger is turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him, Hoſea</hi> 14. 4. But how came wee to bee thus healed? why, <hi>Christ was wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions, Chriſt was broken or bruiſed for our iniquity: The chaſtiſement of our peace was laid upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed, Eſay</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:62458:86"/> 53. 5. Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
            <p>2 The ſecond excellent effect is, that by the very hearing, meditating, and reading, to ſearch into the truth and learning of this benefit of free Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the holy Ghoſt is freely and experimentally given unto us to dwell in us, and to take up our ſouls and bodies to be his bleſſed temples to dwell in us, as theſe and ſuch like Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teach: <hi>Received ye the ſpirit by the works of the Law,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:62458:87"/> or by the hearing of faith?</hi> that is, of free Juſtification preached, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 2. For, <hi>whilſt Peter was preaching of the death and reſurrection of Chriſt,</hi> juſtifying and freely ſaving Gods people, <hi>even whilst he was ſpeaking, the holy Ghost fell on all them which heard the word, Acts</hi> 10. 44. Therefore ſaith S. <hi>Paul, Know you not that your bodies are the temples of the holy Ghost which is in you, 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 16. and 6. 19. For, <hi>if any man have not the ſpirit of Christ, the ſame is none of his, Rom.</hi> 8. 9. For when <hi>Paul</hi> preached the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt, that <hi>from
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:62458:87"/> all things from which they could not be justified by the Law of Moſes, by Christs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth is juſtified: Then the beleevers were filled with joy and with the holy Ghoſt, Acts</hi> 13. 39. 52.</p>
            <p>3. The third excellent effect of Free Juſtification is, that the juſtified perſon is by the holy Ghoſt thus dwelling in him, ſo united and truly married as a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Bride and Queene, ſo effectually unto Chriſt, that he is made a very member of Chriſt, fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone. Therefore did the Apoſtle
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:62458:88"/> ſay, <hi>Know yee not that your bodies are the members of Chriſt? Yea, he that is joyned to the Lord is one ſpirit, 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 15, 17. For ſaith <hi>Paul, As the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of the body, though they be many, yet are but one body: even ſo is Chriſt; for by one ſpirit are we all bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into one body, whether we be bond or free, and have beene all made to drink into one ſpirit, 1 Cor. 12. 12, 13. Now therefore ye are the body of Christ, and members for your part,</hi> verſ. 27. Yea, I ſay, ſo truly and effectually, <hi>that wee are members of his
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:62458:88"/> body, and of his fleſh, and of his bones, Epheſ.</hi> 5. 30. Oh how truly doth the Apoſtle call theſe benefits, thus free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought upon us by the blood of Chriſt, <hi>unſearcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble riches, Eph.</hi> 3. 8. God make us to ſearch into them deeper.</p>
            <p>4 The fourth excellent effect of our free Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, that hereby we are adopted and made the true children, even ſonnes and daughters of the living God. Therefore doth St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſay, <hi>As many as received him,</hi> (namely to juſtifie them by his blood and death) <hi>to them he gave the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:62458:89"/> prerogative or dignity to bee the ſonnes of God: For Chriſt hath redeemed us from under the Law, that wee might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the adoption of ſonnes. And becauſe we are ſonnes, God hath ſent forth the ſpirit of his ſonne into our hearts, to cry Abba, father, Gal.</hi> 4. 5, 6. And therefore S. <hi>Iohn</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out in admiration of this great dignity, ſaid, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what love the Father hath ſhewed toward us, that wee</hi> (things of nothing, <hi>Pſal. 144. 4.) ſhould be called the ſonnes of God. And now we are the ſonnes of God, but it is not made manifeſt what wee ſhall be; but wee know that
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:62458:89"/> when he</hi> (which is the ſon) <hi>ſhall appeare, we ſhall be like him, 1 Iohn</hi> 3. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>5 The fifth excellent effect of this free Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, that by it wee are made aſſured heires of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory. For ſo ſaith S. <hi>Paul, That we being juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by his free grace, are made heires of eternall life, Tit.</hi> 3. 7. For <hi>if we bee children, we are alſo heires, even heires of God, and joint heires with Chriſt, Rom. 8. 17. For whom God justifieth, them he alſo glorifieth, Rom.</hi> 8. 30. And therefore is free Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication called the <hi>justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of life, Rom.</hi> 5. 18.
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:62458:90"/> Wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth thus, <hi>I reckon that the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of this life are not worthy to bee compared with the glory which ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in us, Rom.</hi> 8. 18.</p>
            <p>6. The ſixth excellent effect of free juſtification is, that by it we are made, as the upſhot and fulneſſe of all that our hearts can wiſh, <hi>truly bleſsed.</hi> For (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) David pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth that man or that woman to be a bleſſed man, or a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed woman, to whom the Lord imputeth righteouſneſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, Rom.</hi> 4. 6. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee teſtifieth further to the Galathians, ſaying, <hi>The
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:62458:90"/> Scripture</hi> (that is, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſpeaking in the Scripture) <hi>foreſeeing that God would justifie the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then through faith, preached before this joyfull newes of the Goſpel unto Abraham, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in thee ſhall all the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles bee bleſſed: So that they that bee of this faith,</hi> of free juſtification, <hi>are bleſſed with faithfull Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3. 8, 9. And can our hearts wiſh or deſire any more? This is the royalty of having on the wedding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe freely given us to cleanſe us from our ſecret ſinnes and breaches of the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:62458:91"/> tenth commandement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known unto our ſelves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 12. And to make us, and all our works, both naturall, civill, and religious, pure, clean, &amp; perfectly holy and righteous from all ſpot of ſinne in the ſight of God, freely without workes, or our perfect working of them: as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſaying, <hi>to the pure all things,</hi> that is, our naturall works, and our civill works, and our religious workes, and <hi>all things are pure, Tit. 1. 15. Thus</hi> onely by free ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification <hi>hath Chriſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us from this preſent evill world, according to the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:62458:91"/> will of God, even our father,</hi> Gal. 1. 4. <hi>Thus hath God made us meet to bee partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> Becauſe <hi>he hath</hi> thus <hi>delivered us from the power</hi> or kingdome <hi>of darkneſſe and hath tranſlated us into the Kingdome of his deare ſonne, Col.</hi> 1. 12, 13. Thus our righteouſneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, we are entred into the kingdom of heaven, <hi>Matth. 5. 20. which kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is within us,</hi> Luk. 17. 21. For <hi>the kingdome of heaven is righteouſneſse, and peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt, Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:62458:92"/> 14. 17. And thus if any man, either Preacher, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtian, have ſome true touch, firſt of the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible filthineſſe of the leaſt ſin in Gods ſight, and then of this glorious excellency of free juſtification thus perfectly healing us of it, it will make us to ſay with Saint <hi>Paul: Yea doubtleſſe I count all things but loſſe for the excellency of the knowledg ſake of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and doe count them but dung, that I may make my gain of Christ, and be found in him, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mine owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:62458:92"/> which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, even the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is of God through faith, Phil.</hi> 3. 8, 9. which one Scripture I have now divers times alledged, becauſe it ſo fully deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the markes, or rather the very nature and eſſence of the true ſaving faith. That whoſoever doth in any meaſure of truth feele the ſame with <hi>Paul</hi> in his heart, let him certainely know that he hath eſcaped out of the <hi>moſt dangerous dead Faith,</hi> and hath <hi>Pauls</hi> faith, that is, the true, live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and juſtifying faith,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:62458:93"/> which onely moſt certainly ſaveth him, and glorifieth him. For, <hi>whom God justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, them alſo hee glorifieth, Rom.</hi> 8. 30. And thus much be ſpoken of the two main points of religion, which being thus thorowly loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked into, and deeply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, are the effectuall means to deliver us out of the dead faith, and to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate us into the true, lively, juſtifying, and ſaving faith.</p>
            <p>Now out of theſe two points thus thorowly loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked into, and deeply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, will infallibly flow a third thing; which (as St. <hi>Iohn</hi> teacheth in all his three Epiſtles, is Love;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:62458:93"/> which <hi>Paul</hi> alſo very reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely teſtifieth, ſaying, <hi>For in Christ Ieſus neither cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but faith which is effectuall, operative, or workfull by love.</hi> For the true beleever having by this true faith a feeling of the true love of Chriſt toward him, it onely and infallibly inflames his heart with the true love of Chriſt againe, and of God in Chriſt, and of his whole Church, &amp; of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry child of God in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which true love conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the beleever, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 14. Not onely to doe his vocation diligently, and ſo with <hi>David</hi> to ſerve his
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:62458:94"/> generation faithfully, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 36. (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe teacheth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 13. ſaying, <hi>Brethren, ye have been called unto liberty,</hi> that is, Now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that faith is come, ye are no longer under the whipping Schoole-maſter, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 25. Wherein though ye were heires, yet being as little children, ye differed nothing from ſervants, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 1. Onely, <hi>uſe not your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty for an occaſion to the fleſh, but by love ſerve one another</hi>) but alſo it conſtraineth him to break off from, and to mortifie all ſinne, and ungodly converſation; and to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:62458:94"/> walke freely, cheerfully, ſincerely, and zealouſly in all Gods will and commandements declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to manward, which is true ſanctification. And thus it is moſt true which the eſtabliſhed doctrine of our Church largely teacheth, ſaying, <hi>That this true faith of free juſtification is a thing of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vertue, and wonderfull operation, ſtrength and power, to bring forth all good moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and good works: or elſe it is not the true, lively, juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, but the blind, dead faith, that leaves men in ſin, death, and double damnation,</hi>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:62458:95"/> as theſe and ſuch like Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teach, <hi>Titus</hi> 2. 11. to 15. <hi>For that grace of God,</hi> namely of free juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>bringeth ſalvation,</hi> for nothing brings ſalvation upon men, but onely the grace of free juſtification, and therefore it is called the <hi>iuſtification of life, Rom. 5. 18. hath appeared to all men, and teacheth us dictami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne charitatis,</hi> by the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting power and force of love, <hi>to deny all ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, and righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi> What is the moving or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting cauſe hereof? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:62458:95"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt gave himſelf for us to redeem us from all our iniquities and purge or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie or make</hi> us clean <hi>to be a peculiar people to himſelf, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good works,</hi> verſ. 14. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> pithily expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth alſo to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> chap. 2. 10. ſaying, <hi>For wee are Gods workmanſhip</hi> (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by free juſtification) <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> that is, made by free Juſtification new creatures to Godward, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17. 21. that is, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med anew in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>Gal. 4. 19. unto good workes,</hi> that is, to Sanctification, Repentance, Mortification, Sincerity, and Vniverſall
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:62458:96"/> declarative obedience to all Gods will and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements declaratively to man-ward, <hi>Which God hath fore-ordained that we ſhould walk in them:</hi> Hence it is that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently teſtifieth, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 6, 9. ſaying, <hi>whoſoever is borne of God,</hi> that is, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is iuſtified <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not,</hi> that is, ſinneth not wittingly and willingly, with free ſtream running to ſinne as before his free iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. <hi>For Gods ſeed,</hi> that is, ſome true ſight of Gods pure and righteous nature, infinitely hating the creature defiled with the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:62458:96"/> leaſt ſinne in his ſight, and ſome feeling of the infinite love of Chriſt bleeding out his bloud and life to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him; this ſeed <hi>remaineth in him, and hee cannot ſinne,</hi> that is, hee cannot lead ſo diſſolute a converſation in ſinne, as he did before, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is born of God,</hi> that is, Becauſe of a wilde crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, he (by free iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is made a perfect good tree to Godward. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee cannot chooſe but bring forth the good fruit to man-ward of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This is largely taught in the whole fifth and ſixth chapters of the Epiſtle to
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:62458:97"/> the <hi>Romanes,</hi> where it is ſhewed, that free juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the cauſe, and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation as the effect, doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes follow unſeparably one the other. Hence it is that S. <hi>Iames</hi> 2. 14. doth ſo ſharply taunt carnall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of free juſtification, ſaying, <hi>What doth it profit, my brethren, for a man to ſay, hee hath faith, and hath not works. Can that faith ſave him?</hi> No, <hi>But ſhew me thy faith by thy works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here mark, how he ſaith not, ſhew God thy faith by thy works, nor ſhew thy ſelfe thy faith by thy works; but <hi>ſhew me,</hi> that
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:62458:97"/> am thy Chriſtian Miniſter, that have the charge of thy ſoule, and have the keyes given me of the Kingdom of heaven to binde thee and looſe thee, <hi>Matth. 16. 19. ſhew him thy faith by thy works,</hi> or thy Chriſtian neighbours that dwell round about thee, and deale with thee, <hi>ſhew them thy faith</hi> (namely that it is true and ſound) <hi>by thy works,</hi> that is, by thy ſanctified words and deeds that flow from love and a godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. <hi>For know, O thou vaine man, that faith without ſuch works is dead: Seeſt thou not that by the example
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:62458:98"/> of Abraham and Rahab, that faith was effectuall, operative, and powerfull by works, and by their works was their faith made perfect,</hi> that is, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee ſound and true. <hi>But as the body without the ſpirit is dead, ſo faith alſo without ſanctified words and deeds flowing from true love, is dead,</hi> verſe 26. This even Chriſt himſelfe teacheth alſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 16. ſaying, <hi>Let your light,</hi> namely of free Juſtification, <hi>ſo ſhine before men:</hi> how ſhine? by ſanctification, <hi>that they may ſee,</hi> the beames of, <hi>your good works, and glorifie your father which is in heaven.</hi> Thus a
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:62458:98"/> Chriſtian (as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaks) is made perfect, and entire, lacking nothing: why? becauſe he is <hi>pure as the Sunne</hi> to Godward by free Juſtification, <hi>faire as the Moone</hi> to Manward by ſanctification, <hi>and terrible as an army with banners by zeale of Gods glory, Cant.</hi> 6. 9.</p>
            <p>This is the eſtabliſhed doctrine of our Church: this is true Proteſtancy: this is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to goe with a right foot to the truth of the Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 14. If any man can ſhew me a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way, I will endeavour to run with him in it. But if this be the old way that we
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:62458:99"/> bee commanded of God, <hi>Ier.</hi> 6. 16. to ask after, that old <hi>Abraham</hi> and all the ancient ſaved fathers walked in, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. And not only the old way, but alſo the good way which only bringeth reſt and peace unto our ſoules: For <hi>being juſtified by faith, wee have peace with God, Rom.</hi> 5. 1. Then let us embrace one another in the truth of this way. Let no man be ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and obſtinate to his owne damnation, as to ſay with the ſtubborne loſt Jewes, <hi>Wee will not walk in it, Ier.</hi> 6. 16.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:62458:99"/>
            <head>Abrahams Stepps of Faith.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The two maine ſaving points of Religion, the deep conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by Gods holy ſpirit, and thorough marking whereof, cauſeth our true converſion, peace of conſcience, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of free ſalvation by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>Being the expreſſe word of God, and the eſtabliſhed
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:62458:100"/> Doctrine of our Church, at the reſtoring of the pure Goſpel of Chriſt into this land; enjoyned to the Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by the godly autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and publick conſent of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to be taught to the people for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Errours and Popery, for the quieting of conſciences in the matters of religion, for the beating down of ſin and all vitiouſneſs of life out of the Land: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of theſe two main points, mentioned <hi>Iohn 17. 3. This is eternall life to know thee the only true,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:62458:100"/> God, and Ieſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FIrſt, that the filthineſſe of ſinne is ſuch to Gods infinite, pure and righteous nature, that God cannot but deteſt, curſe, and abhor the creature that hath any ſin in his ſight, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Eſay 59. 2. Deut. 27. 26. 2 Pet. 2. 4. Rom. 5. 12. Deut.</hi> 28. 15. to 20. Becauſe ſin being ſpirituall high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the higheſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 23. and the Image of the Devill doth make the creature ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually foule, filthy, loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:62458:101"/> and abominable in Gods ſight, though no curſe and puniſhment ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low upon the ſame, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Iob 15. 15, 16. Hab. 1. 13. Mark</hi> 7. 20. to 25. Yea and makes the beſt good works of the moſt ſanctified children of God to be ſin, and all their righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of ſanctification to be as ſoule, filthy, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous rags, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Rom. 7. 18. Eſay 64. 6. Rom. 4. 5. Gal.</hi> 3. 22. And we muſt look ſo deepely into the truth of this firſt point, that wee bee throughly affected
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:62458:101"/> with the ſame as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay</hi> was, chap. 6. 5. the neglect whereof is the main cauſe that the huge multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, yea of many zealous workers, doe periſh in the dead Faith: Becauſe they know not God, that is, his righteouſneſſe, that is, his holy and righteous nature, where in we were moſt blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the fall of <hi>Adam, Eſay</hi> 46. 12. 13. this is the firſt point.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point is, that by the power of Gods im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation we are ſo clothed with the wedding-garment of Chriſts perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that all our ſinnes
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:62458:102"/> being done away and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed out of Gods ſight, we and all our works are freely made, of unjuſt, juſt before God, that is, perfectly holy and righteous, from all ſpot of ſin, in the ſight of God freely, by faith only with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures doe teach, <hi>Dan. 9. 24. Eſay 45. 24, 25. Eſay 53. 11. Rom. 5. 16, 17, 18. 2 Cor. 5. 21. Rom. 5. 19. Rom. 3. 23, 24, 28. Tit.</hi> 1. 15.</p>
            <p>Hereby we may ſee that the parts of free Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are two: Firſt, that by the blood and wedding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe all our ſins
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:62458:102"/> are done away &amp; aboliſhed, not out of us, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 8. (that we may live by faith) <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. but from before God, or out of Gods ſight, 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 22. and we and all our works are made pure and cleane from all ſin freely in the ſight of God, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Eſay 44. 22. Iohn 1. 29. Eſay 43. 25. 1 Iohn 1. 7. Revel. 1. 5, 6. Heb. 9. 26. Act. 10. 15. Act. 15. 8, 9. Heb.</hi> 1. 3. and 9. 13, 14. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 22. And this was the Prophet <hi>Eſay's</hi> remedy againſt the filthineſſe of his ſin in Gods ſight, chap. 6. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the ſame
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:62458:103"/> wedding-garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe doth alſo make us, and all our works of unjuſt, juſt before God, that is, perfectly holy and righteous, from all ſpot of ſin, in the ſight of God freely without our perfect workings, as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Eſay 61. 10. Rom. 3. 21, 22. Eph. 5. 26, 27. Rom. 5. 17, 19. Rev. 3. 18. Col.</hi> 1. 22. &amp; 2. 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 4. &amp; 9. 30. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 14. And mark how I ſay, not only we our perſons, but alſo all our works, both naturall, civill, and religious, and all our ſanctified actions, which by their imperfections are in
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:62458:103"/> themſelves foule and filthy, are by free Juſtification made ſo pure and clean, yea ſo perfectly holy and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and thereby ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and perfectly well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God, that they are all (as I ſaid) both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, civill, and religious actions, like the excellent ſacrifice of righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> and works of <hi>Enoch, Noah, Abraham,</hi> as theſe and ſuch like Scriptures teach, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 4, 5, 6, 7, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet. 2. 5. Heb. 13. 16. Act. 15. 9. Hoſ. 14. 2. Heb. 13. 15. Phil. 4. 18. Heb.</hi> 13. 20, 21. This is the Kingdom of heaven ſet up here on earth by Chriſt,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:62458:104"/> ſo much ſpoken of in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth. 11. 11, 12. Matth. 6. 33. Rom.</hi> 4. 17, 18. this is to know Jeſus Chriſt whom the Father hath ſent, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 3.</p>
            <p>Now God will have this benefit of Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, juſtifying both our perſons and works, to be received and enjoyed by faith only for divers Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt, that it may be free, only for taking it by faith. Secondly, that it may be to the praiſe and glory of his grace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 4, 5, 6. Thirdly, that he that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth, may glory only in the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 45. 25.
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:62458:104"/> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30, 31. Fourthly, that none may boaſt, but be humbled in his beſt works of ſanctification, <hi>Eph. 2. 9. Rom.</hi> 7. 24. Fifthly, that the promiſe of inheritance of Righteouſneſſe and Life might be ſure to all the ſeed <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 16. Sixthly, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially becauſe none ſhall be ſaved but the true chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as theſe Scriptures teach, <hi>Rom. 2. 28, 29. Rom 4. 11, 12, 16. Gal.</hi> 3. 16. 29. But none are the true children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but ſuch as walk in the ſteps of the faith of their father <hi>Abraham, Rom.</hi> 4. 12. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is exceeding need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:62458:105"/> yea only neceſſary to know what thoſe ſteps are; hereof the Apoſtle doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently deſcribe unto us the juſtifying faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Rom.</hi> 4. 17. to 22. that we may not be ignorant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee will be wilfull in our owne juſt damnation, what thoſe ſteps of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> faith were, which were theſe foure.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſtep is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and ground of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> faith, namely that he beleeved in him that quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens the dead, and calleth thoſe things that be not, as though they were, verſe 17. that is, he makes the things
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:62458:105"/> that be not to have as true a being before himſelfe, by his call, or as he cals them, as if they had a viſible being to our eyes; and ſo faith is a true ſubſtance and being of things that are not ſeen, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 1. This is the firſt Step.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Step is the battell of his faith, namely that <hi>Abraham</hi> againſt, or contrary to hope, beleeved under hope, according as it was ſpoken: So ſhall thy ſeed be, verſe 18. that is, contrary to all hope of what he ſaw and felt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in that he was as good as dead to the having of
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:62458:106"/> children, and yet he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under hope of Gods word, according as it was ſpoken; not that hee, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his deadneſſe to children, ſhould yet have three or four children: but, thou art ſo fruitfull before me, that thy ſeed ſhall be as the ſtars of heaven for mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: In this was the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of his faith, in that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hope he beleeved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hope.</p>
            <p>The third ſtep is the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory of his faith, namely, that he not weake in faith, conſidered not, but pulled back his eyes from his own body now dead, and thereby
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:62458:106"/> impoſſible to reaſon to have children: and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not the deadneſſe of <hi>Sarahs</hi> wombe, who was more unlikely to have chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren than he: neither did he doubt of the promiſe of God by unbeliefe, but was ſtrengthened in faith: and thus got the victory in his faith, verſe 19.</p>
            <p>The fourth ſtep is the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of faith, namely, that he gave glory to God, that is, confeſſed in his heart the truth of God ſpeaking, though he ſpake impoſſible things to reaſon, and preſent ſenſe and feeling: and alſo glorified the power of God
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:62458:107"/> as all-ſufficient to doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible things as hee had ſpoken it. Being fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that hee which had ſpoken, though it ſeemed never ſo impoſſible, muſt needs be true of his word, and alſo was able to doe it. Becauſe hee hath power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to do all impoſsible things to reaſon, and ſo gave glory to God, verſ. 20, 21. and therfore it was imputed unto him for righteouſnes verſ. 22.</p>
            <p>Now this was not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for <hi>Abraham</hi> onely, that it was imputed unto him for righteouſneſſe, verſ. 23. but alſo for us, to whom it
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:62458:107"/> ſhall be imputed for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe that truſt in the death of Chriſt, for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing of our ſins; and in his reſurrection for our free and full iuſtification, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as the true ſonnes and daughters of <hi>Abraham</hi> wee do imitate in our free iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, and ſo doe walke in the ſteps of the faith of our father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> thus or after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Firſt is the foundation and ground of our faith of free iuſtification, namely, to beleeve in God, that by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting his ſons righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, quickens them that
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:62458:108"/> are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 5. How? by making us that are not iuſt and righteous, to be by his call, as truly and perfectly iuſt and righteous in Gods ſight, as he calls us, as if we did ſee and feele our ſelves perfectly holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in outward ſenſe and feeling, and this is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and ground of our free iuſtification, which cauſeth the ſubſtance and very being of free iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 26. though we doe ſee no ſuch things with bodily eyes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 1. 3.</p>
            <p>Secondly followes the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:62458:108"/> battel in our faith of free iuſtification, that wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all hope of what we ſee and feel in our ſelvs, whereby we ſee and feel our own righteouſneſſe to be as filthy menſtruous rags, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 64. 6. do yet beleeve under hope of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that we of uniuſt are made iuſt before God, that is, our bodies and ſouls are made perfectly holy and righteous from all ſpot of ſin in the ſight of God free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without works, according to that which is ſpoken, <hi>As by the diſobedience of one man many were made ſinners; ſo by the obedience of one ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:62458:109"/> be made righteous, Rom.</hi> 5. 19. according as it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt the Son of God doth make us clean from all ſin, 1 Ioh.</hi> 1. 7. this is the battell in the faith of our free iuſtification, that againſt hope we beleeve under hope.</p>
            <p>Thirdly followes the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, that we not weak in faith doe not conſider, but pull back our eyes from the free conſideration of our bodies which we feel dead in ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 24. nor yet conſider the deadneſſe of our natures by originall corruption dwelling in us, like <hi>Sarahs</hi> unfruitfull
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:62458:109"/> wombe: neither will wee doubt of this iuſtifying promiſe by unbelief, but be ſtrengthened in faith, that our bodies and ſoules are made perfectly holy and righteous from all ſpot of ſin in the ſight of God free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And thus we get with <hi>Abraham</hi> the victory in our faith of free iuſtification.</p>
            <p>Fourthly follows the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of faith of free iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that wee give glory to God; being fully aſſured that he which hath ſpoken it, that by his Sons bloud he hath made us pure and clean, yea perfectly holy and righteous from all ſpot
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:62458:110"/> of ſin in his own ſight free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Heb. 10. 14. Col.</hi> 1. 22. muſt needs be true of his word: and alſo able to doe it, becauſe hee is almighty and hath power ſufficient to doe all things, to reaſon, ſenſe, and feeling impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Matth. 19. 26. Luk.</hi> 1. 37. and ſo gives glory to God, which is the Religion of Religions, the worſhip of worſhips, the ſervice of ſervices, the ſacrifice of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, the wiſdome of wiſdomes, the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of righteouſneſſes, without which all other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and worſhip are ſinne and abomination in the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:62458:110"/> ſight of God, <hi>Luk. 16. 15. Heb.</hi> 10. 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Thus we walking by free juſtification in the ſteps of our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> there follow thereof theſe two great and excellent effects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, perfect reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and peace with God, <hi>for being juſtified by faith we have peace with God, Rom.</hi> 5. 1 And all evils and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ſin being done away, that we may ſerve God without fear, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 74. we are truly bleſſed, <hi>for as many as are of faith of free iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, are bleſſed with faithful Abraham, Gal.</hi> 38. 9. and together with faithfull
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:62458:111"/> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> are made ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently rich with all tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall riches, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. 2, 5, 6. and alſo ſpirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall riches which <hi>Abraham</hi> chiefly rejoyced in, <hi>Ioh. 8. 56. 2. Cor. 8. 9. Heb.</hi> 11. 9, 10. yea heirs of the whole world onely by this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of faith: for (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) the promiſe that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> ſhould be the heire of the world, was not given unto <hi>Abraham</hi> or to his ſeed through the Law, but through the righteouſneſſe of faith, <hi>Rom. 4. 13. 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 22, 23. For if they that are of the Law be heires, faith is made void, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:62458:111"/> is made of none effect, verſ. 14. Therefore it is of faith, that it may come by grace, and the promiſe might be ſure to all the ſeed, not to that only which is of the Law, that is, to the Jewes onely; but alſo to that which is of the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that is, to the Gentiles alſo, who is the father of us all, verſ. 16.</p>
            <p>The ſecond effect is, that this faith of free juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this walking in the ſteps of our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> cauſeth us infallibly to walke in the ſteps of the works of our father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> whereby like <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:62458:112"/> without the Law of the ten Commandements, we walk holily, ſoberly, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in all Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements declaratively to manward, being zealous of good workes, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12, 13. &amp;c. By all this it is clear that the practice, and preachings, and bookes of ſuch Miniſters are exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bad and dangerous, as by a prepoſterous zeale of works and well-doings, ſpeake little or nothing of faith of free juſtification; thinking by the dead faith it is an eaſie matter to walk in the ſteps of the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but that all the
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:62458:112"/> hardneſſe lyeth in workings and well-doings; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do call for a good life, and the doing of all holy duties zealouſly, but prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterouſly, before people be ſure by comfort and joy of free iuſtification, that they walke in the ſteps of the faith our father <hi>Abraham:</hi> ſuch Miniſters (I ſay) in ſtead of making people the true children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of the free woman <hi>Sarah,</hi> do make them baſtard children of the bond-woman <hi>Hagar,</hi> that muſt be caſt out of the inheritance, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 21. In ſtead of making them the children of the promiſe,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:62458:113"/> they make them children that will be under the Law and workes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 21. In ſtead of making them chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of faith and of the bleſsing, they make them the children of workes and of the curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10. In ſtead of working peace with God in their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, they worke unquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, fears, and troubles of conſcience about workes: In ſtead of making the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of righteouſneſſe and life to come by grace, and the promiſe to be ſure to all the ſeed, they make it to come as it were by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and the promiſe to be
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:62458:113"/> unſure and doubtfull to all the ſeed: In ſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them heires of all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings temporall and eternall with faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> they make them as much as in them lyeth heires of all evils and puniſhments, with the deceitfull work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men mentioned 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13, 14, 15. In ſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to walke in the true good workes of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> they make them at the beſt but to walk in the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming good works of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouter ſort of Scribes and Phariſees, that is in a legall baſtard ſanctification, which is of high eſteem and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:62458:114"/> amongſt men, but is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy abomination in the ſight of God. <hi>Luk. 18. 19. Rom. 10. 2, 3. Luk. 18. 19. 11. 12. Act. 22. 3, 4. &amp; 26. 5, 7. &amp;</hi> 13. 50.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <head>The true Treaſure of the Heart.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 21.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>FOr where your treaſure is, there will your hearts be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo:</hi> ſo that if the wedding garment of Chriſts perfect righteouſneſſe making us perfectly holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous from all ſpot of ſin in
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:62458:114"/> the ſight of God freely, by faith onely, without works and working, be our treaſure, there will be our hearts and tongues alſo; and then our hearts ſtand right to Chriſt, and our tongues to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers chaſt virgins to Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2, 3. and true chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and of that Jeruſalem which is above, the mother of us all, and we ſhall never bee caſt out as baſtard children, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 21, to 31. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 28, 29, 21, 22. &amp; chap. 2. 10. <hi>Heb. 10. 14. Rom. 5. 10, 21. Col.</hi> 1. 12, 13. Becauſe wee bring forth a true godly life, only for and by the joy and excellency
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:62458:115"/> of <hi>Free Iuſtification,</hi> not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally but rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and embraced, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12, 13, 14. But if Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, repentance, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, mortification, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall obedience, holy &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous walking in all Gods commandements, ſincerity, and new life, and ſuch like works bee our treaſure and diamond, then there will be our hearts and tongues alſo to extoll, dignifie, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort the ſame, whereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing by legall arguments but a falſe baſtard ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 6. our hearts ſtand adulterouſly to Chriſt; and all ſuch preaching and
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:62458:115"/> holineſſe produced thereby is but idolatry and unbelief, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13, 14, 15. and ſuch Preachers by miſunderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and darkning <hi>Free Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,</hi> do <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ſtand accurſed by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, though in all other gifts and graces they bee like Angels from heaven, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8, 9. and ever in danger of ſudden death, <hi>Rev. 3. 13. Gal.</hi> 5. 12. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beware of the <hi>dead Faith,</hi> which being varniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and gilt over with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous zeal and opinion of holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before God, by walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:62458:116"/> doth give Chriſt and <hi>Free Iuſtification</hi> a <hi>Iudas his kiſſe, Rom.</hi> 10. 3. And yet ſuch Preachers tremble not as they go up into the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, although their preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings be both idolatrous and trayterous.</p>
            <q>Here is life and death, who hath an ear to regard it?</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62458:116"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
